<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Omnibus &amp; singulis Affording matter profitable for all men, necessarie for euery man; alluding to a fathers aduice or last will to his sonne. Now published for the vse of all men, and particularly of those that doe inhabit Great Brittaine and Ireland.</title>
            <author>Scot, Patrick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 62 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11616</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21858.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854770</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854770</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20214</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11616)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20214)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 975:9 or 2070:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Omnibus &amp; singulis Affording matter profitable for all men, necessarie for euery man; alluding to a fathers aduice or last will to his sonne. Now published for the vse of all men, and particularly of those that doe inhabit Great Brittaine and Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Scot, Patrick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: P.S., i.e. Patrick Scot.</note>
                  <note>Another edition, revised and enlarged, of STC 21858.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21858 at reel 975:9.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnibus &amp; ſingulis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AFFORDING MATTER PROFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TABLE FOR ALL men, neceſſarie for euery man; Alluding to a Fathers aduice or laſt Will to his ſonne. Now publiſhed for the vſe of all men, and particularly of thoſe <hi>that doe inhabit</hi> Great Brittaine <hi>and</hi> IRELAND.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>GALAT. 10.6.</bibl> 
               <hi>While we haue time, let vs doe good to all men, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to thoſe of the houſhold of Faith.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>Hoc ab homine exigitur, vt profit hominibus; ſi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, multis; ſi minùs, paucis; ſi minùs, proximis; ſi minùs, ſibi; <bibl>
                  <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by WILLIAM STANSBY. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Sacred, <hi>Chriſtian, truely</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and Mighty Prince, <hi>IAMES, King of Great Britaine, France, and</hi> Ireland, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne. As your Maieſtie (by due) haue the firſt place <hi>inter Omnes &amp; Singulos,</hi> to whoſe Patrocinie this imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture birth is dedicated, ſo by the Law you haue the chiefeſt intereſt in it.</p>
            <p>I doe confeſſe, moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb facs="tcp:20214:3"/> SIR, I haue borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the ouer-flowing Source of your Maieſties Princely and Learned <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the beſt matter contained in it, and for ſatisfaction do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offer reſtitution with ſome ſmal intereſt (although in a farre more baſe coyne.)</p>
            <p>As your Maieſties knowne Clemencie, puts me in ſome hope of pardon, for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, in borrowing the principall; ſo thoſe eminent and<note n="*" place="margin">Parum eſt optare tantae Virtuti tantae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Pietati quem longiſſimum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat Vitae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſum: fac De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us vt quod op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum human<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> generi dediſti, permaneat in ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum: nam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que laudes eius referre Vires ſuppetunt, neque paruum Carmen recipit tanta Maieſtas, neque meus audet rem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentare Pudor, quam <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ires fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re recuſant: hoc tamen mihi aſſerere liceat prauum indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numque eſt, non admirari Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m omni ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miratione dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſimum.</note> admired Kingly Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, reſident in your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Perſon, make mee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, your Maieſtie will rather accept of this ſuper-plus (being worſe then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) then reiect the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt offering that is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated
<pb facs="tcp:20214:3"/> (vpon the Altar of a dutifull and ſincere affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) to your Maieſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; if, what I haue added, can onely yeeld vnto your Maieſtie that Satifaction (whereof I much doubt) that an<note n="*" place="margin">Dauid in Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic. Mercer.</note> Ignorant Arabian Woman did giue vnto the Learned Iewes Rabbies, who (by calling for a Broom or Beſome) did bring them to the knowledge of an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure place in the Prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 14.23.</note> I ſhall thinke my Labours happie; and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer (as I and all your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Subiects, by the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of your happy gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are dutifully bound) I ſhall euer earneſtly intreat the Almightie, that your Maieſtie may continue long
<pb facs="tcp:20214:4"/> and proſperouſly to raigne ouer vs, and after <hi>Methuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> age, by a happie ende may change your Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Crowne with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of endleſſe Glorie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maiesties Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Subiect, <hi>PATRIK SCOT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:4"/>
            <head>To the High and Mightie, CHARLES, <hi>Prince of Great</hi> Britaine, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S God hath moſt aboundantly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your Highnes, in honouring you on both ſides with two<note n="a" place="margin">Dos eſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gna Parentum Virtus, <hi>Horat. Carm. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Ode.</hi> 24.</note> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Parents, whoſe Memorie (as now) will be euer deſeruedly honoured: ſo it is iuſtly expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that their Royal Vertues (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie<note n="b" place="margin">Precioſa Principum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia &amp; Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus quae ante annos viget. <hi>Caſſiador.</hi>
               </note> happily begun) ſhall be renewed in your Highneſſe (as in a more<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Euripid. Meleagr.</note> liuely monument,
<pb facs="tcp:20214:5"/> then of Marble or Braſſe) and (if it were poſsible) in well doing and<note n="d" place="margin">Quod prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibilius aut pulchrius mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Deorum quàm Sanctus &amp; Dijs ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Princeps. <hi>Plin. in Paneg. Traian.</hi>
               </note> pietie you ſhall not onely paralell, but ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe them.</p>
            <p>Your Kingly and Learned Father <hi>Dauid</hi> hath ſo broken the Ice to your Highneſſe, his beloued young <hi>Salomon,</hi> (by laying ſuch foundations for the gouernement of your ſelfe and your <hi>Iſrael</hi> after him) that whatſoeuer can be added, is but <hi>inferre lumen mortale ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente ſole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which only reaſon, I haue preſumed (with <hi>Phaeton,</hi> truſting to my borrow'd wings) to preſent vnto your Highnes this deformed Portraiture, drawn from the Paterne (of the<note n="e" place="margin">Vinci eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſcens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles tertio colore line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſecuit nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſubtilitati locum, <hi>Plinius l.</hi> 35. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Apelles</hi> like Picture) of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that
<pb facs="tcp:20214:5"/> by the view of ſuch a diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Monſter, your Highneſſe may proſecute the imitation of that Worke, that no Man (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept vnmatchable<note n="f" place="margin">Pyrgotelis ita omnium ſculptorum peritiſſimus, vt Alexander e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dixit ne quis eum quam il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſculperer, <hi>Plin. l.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 37. <hi>Appoli. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Florid. Cicero Epiſt.</hi> 12. <hi>ad Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al. Max. c.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Pyrgote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> that hath ingrauen it vpon the Marble<note n="g" place="margin">Nihil eſt accepta Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te quod (mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali animo aut manu) immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tale queri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, <hi>Val. Max.</hi>
               </note> of inobliterable Vertue) is able to equalize.</p>
            <p>If it will pleaſe your Highnes to Grace theſe my idle Labours with<note n="h" place="margin">Laetiſſima Principis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies &amp; amabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis vultus in omnium ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorum ore oculis &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſedet, <hi>Plin. in Paneg. Traian.</hi>
               </note> a ſmiling countenance: (being all I deſire) I ſhall thinke my Idleneſſe fortunate, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour hereafter to finde out ſome other ſubiect, more Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie your Princely entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus Sir (renewing the oath of my loyall ſeruice to your Highneſſe by my pen, that formerly I did ſolemnely ſweare by the holding vp of my hand in a ſteele Gantlet, now aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:20214:6"/> to bee ſeene for rust) I doe humbly take my leaue, and ſhall euer remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe dutifull and humble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, PATRIK SCOT.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:6"/>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:7"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:7"/>
            <head>Libri ad Sereniſsimam Mag. Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanniae <hi>ANNAM</hi> Reginam defunctam, Proſopopeia.</head>
            <l>QVid me purpureo circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dedit autor amictu?</l>
            <l>Quid micat aurato margine ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s?</l>
            <l>Quid iunat argutis ſapientum floribus, omnes</l>
            <l>Ornaſſe <hi>Aonidum,</hi> morte fremente choros?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Anna Iouis</hi> Proles, Regni decus <hi>Anna</hi> Britanni,</l>
            <l>Spes mihi, ſpes Orbi, te morie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te cadit.</l>
            <l>Tu multum, quaeſita mihi virtutis imago,</l>
            <l>Tu vitae columen, praeſidium<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> meae.</l>
            <l>Cui meta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propera moribundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſorte remittis?</l>
            <l>Cui me ſolicitum, deſeris ante diem?</l>
            <l>Illa tui ſplendens genij praeſentia, ſaeuas</l>
            <l>Inuidiae poterat ſternere ſola minas;</l>
            <l>Nunc mihi deſerto tutela incerta; carebit</l>
            <l>Nulla dies lachrymis, vulnere nulla dies.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:8"/>
            <head>Sereniſsimae ANNAE Reginae, Reſponſio conſolatoria.</head>
            <l>COeleſtes animas triſti quid voce laceſsis?</l>
            <l>Ereptas Orbi, num reuocare potes?</l>
            <l>Quid tibi ſpem quereris deiectam? quidue minaces,</l>
            <l>Inuidiae rictus docte libelle times?</l>
            <l>Ecce triumphator, morbos morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Monarcha</l>
            <l>Qui vincit, thalamo pars viduata meo,</l>
            <l>Contra letiferos ſapiens te proteget hoſtes,</l>
            <l>Maior &amp; inuidia; maior &amp; hoſte tuo.</l>
            <l>Exurgens tibi fautor erit mihi charus Iulus,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>CAROLVS</hi> Imperij dextera chara mei;</l>
            <l>Altera ſpes <hi>ELIZA</hi> tibi, ſpes altera totus</l>
            <l>Nobilium coetus, qua tibi terra patet.</l>
            <l>Nec ſacra Progenies Regum te ſola fouebit,</l>
            <l>Sed ſacra virtutum ſymbola quiſquis amat.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:8"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE Dedicatorie, <hi>OMNIBVS ET</hi> SINGVLIS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Do (in all duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) preſent vnto the bar of your Mighty, High, Gracious, Reuerend, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, Worſhipfull, and Fauourable Cenſure, theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll digeſted labours of ſome few idle houres:</p>
            <p>In doing whereof (encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged
<pb facs="tcp:20214:9"/> by the confidence I haue in your powerfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trocinie) I haue made choice rather to expoſe my Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice-like skill in the ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of ſuch an Architect, my preſumption in the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and Dedication; to baſe detracting<note n="*" place="margin">Detractio eſt ſtultorum the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurus, quem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n lingua-gerunt, <hi>Auſon.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Zoylus,</hi> or enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note n="*" place="margin">nu dia non in alio quàm in degeneri, minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to &amp; ieiuno a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo, ſibi domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillum parat, <hi>Val. Max.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Momus;</hi> then either the Learned ſhould want this Widdowes Symboll of my good will, (more fit to inlarge their Libraries then knowledge) or the Ignorant be defrauded of the benefit, that (with ſmall paines) they may reape, by peruſing of ſo eaſie a taske.</p>
            <p>I haue rather approoued the Greeke Prouerbe (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) by confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Matter, within ſo
<pb facs="tcp:20214:9"/> ſmall precinct; then follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe that dayly loſe themſelues in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Bookes, that are ſent abroad,<note n="*" place="margin">Venialis fit apud aures ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras veritatis aſperitas, <hi>Sidon Apoll.</hi>
               </note> tending rather to ſhew the Authors skill in refined and affected Phraſes, in light Subiects, their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Contention in indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Controuerſies, their vnchriſtian diſpoſition, in Worme-wood taſting Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme, then to preferre ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance before ſhaddow, loue of truth before vnprofitable ambiguities, or charitable Iudgement before accurſed ſcandall.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Palaton Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merum,</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentem expri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebat, Poetas verò reuquos quae ille eieciſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t abſorbentes, <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Rhod. l. 11. cap. 44.</hi>
               </note>What I haue borrowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this Treatiſe, I haue done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>Lege talionis,</hi> (thoſe that I haue made vſe of, hauing formerly beene beholding
<pb facs="tcp:20214:10"/> to others;) and haue reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it again with the intereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of thankfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>But leſt I ſhould doe lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto thoſe, that (vnaduiſed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly) did build the Gates big<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger then the Citie, I humbly take my leaue; and ſhall eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A Loyall Subiect, A tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> honourer of my Sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riours, and of ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue in all men,</hi> P. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> FATHER HIS EPISTLE (Or Introduction to the inſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) to his SONNE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Doe find (by the Law <hi>Falcidia</hi>) if the Child committeth any fault, for want of Education, the Father was puniſhed.</p>
            <p>That I ſhould not bee
<pb facs="tcp:20214:11"/> lyable to that (and a more ſupreme) Law, I haue (from your Infancy) been carefull to haue you ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently grounded in theſe Rudiments, that doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne both your Spirituall and Ciuill conuerſation.</p>
            <p>But now in regard of your more riper Age, the time approching, that you muſt act thoſe things (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtage of the World) that either hath or ſhall now be taught you, for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the dutie I owe you, and inabling you in thoſe ſeruices, your Maker, Prince, and Country chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth
<pb facs="tcp:20214:11"/> of you; J doe ſend you this <hi>MANVSCRIPT</hi> (which I did write for my owne priuate vſe) and now beſtow it vpon you, as the greateſt (and without doubt the beſt) portion I am able to giue you; It doth ſhortly contayne the knowledge of God, as hee hath reuealed himſelfe in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The way to ſerue him aright (I meane in the higheſt perfection that the<note n="*" place="margin">Mortalis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio non patitur hominem ab om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni maculo purit, <hi>Lact. l. 6. de ve. 10 Cultu.</hi>
               </note> corrupt nature of the ſonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> is able to vndergoe.)</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:20214:12"/> Precepts and Counſels, as may (by the carefull ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the firſt part) with great facilitie, bring you to the knowledge of your ſelfe in the ſeuerall duties that are required of a<note n="*" place="margin">O ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> beatus, tu de cuius culmine datur amicis lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titia, poſteris glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, vegetis &amp; alacri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum, deſidibus &amp; pig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s incita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Sidon. Apol. lib. 4. Epiſt. 4.</hi>
               </note> perfect man.</p>
            <p>Receiue it then with ſuch an heart as I giue it you, remember that there is nothing more odious then fruitleſſe old age, and that no tree beares fruit in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumne, but that which bloſſometh in the Spring: to the end your Age may bee profitable and loden with fruit, indeuour that
<pb facs="tcp:20214:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> your youth may be ſtudious and flowred with the bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes of Learning and Obſeruation.</p>
            <p>Thus charging you (by the<note n="*" place="margin">Vitioſi ſunt oculi qui lucem reformidant, percaeci qui non vident, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentibus non obedire, impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas eſt; non ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere, inſania, <hi>Senec. lib. 3. de Benef.</hi>
               </note> Fatherly authoritie I haue ouer you, you dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently peruſe, in your life and conuerſation carefully practiſe thoſe things that are in this Treatiſe ſet downe; I commend you to his Grace, whoſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are neuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to them that put their truſt in him.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iunij, XVIIII M.D.C.XIX.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:13"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. CLeobulus,</hi> Deum Conſule.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2. Chilon,</hi> Noſce teipſum.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. Thales,</hi> Vide cui aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaris.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4. Periander,</hi> Iram tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5. Bias,</hi> Benè vixit, qui paucis contentus.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6. Pitacus,</hi> Ne quid nimis.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7. Solon,</hi> Reſpice finem.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20214:13"/>
            <head>OMNIBVS <hi>ET</hi> SINGVLIS: Affording matter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for all Men, and <hi>neceſſarie for euery Man.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or<note n="*" place="margin">Stirpe ſubla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, aut non ſunt reliqua, aut ſi ſunt, ſine emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſunt, quia ſine Capite nihil conſtat, <hi>Saluian l. 6. de Prouid.</hi>
                  </note> laying the firſt foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (without which al other grounds are to no effect.)</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Per viſibiles viſibilium for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas peruenitur ad inuiſibiles viſibilium cauſas, aſcenſus praeſtatur ad inuiſibiles ſubſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tias, &amp; ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um dignoſcenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturas, <hi>Coel. Rhod. lib. 25.</hi>
                  </note> That there is a GOD
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20214:14"/> Omnipotent, Mercifull and Iuſt, Gods Works doe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently demonſtrate.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 1.1.</note>If he build, it is a World: if he be angrie for the ſinnes of the World,<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 7.17.</note> hee ſends a Deluge. If hee will ſhew the loue hee beares to the World,<note n="e" place="margin">Matt. 2.1.</note> he ſends his Sonne,<note n="f" place="margin">Matt. 27.57.</note> and ſuffers him to dye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſſe, to ſaue the World: If hee will reward the godly, it is with<note n="g" place="margin">Luke 23.43.</note> 
                  <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe;</hi> when hee armes, the<note n="*" place="margin">2. King. 6.17.</note> Angels march vpon the head of his Troupes,<note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 17.6.</note> the Elements are the Marſhals of his Campe, the Rocks remooue from their Centre and follow to giue it Water,<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 13.21.</note> the Cloudes guide by day, and Pillars of fire by night,<note n="k" place="margin">Exod. 14.19.</note> the Sea opens to giue
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20214:14"/> them paſſage,<note n="l" place="margin">Ioſh. 10.12.</note> and the Sun ſtayes to end their victories. To inlarge the wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Works,<note n="m" place="margin">Num. 22.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> Aſſe ſhall ſpeake, and reprooue his Maſter:<note n="n" place="margin">Iohn 2.9.</note> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters turne into Wine, the<note n="o" place="margin">Matt. 9.22.</note> dead are raiſed to life,<note n="p" place="margin">Matt. 20.24.</note> the Blind ſee,<note n="q" place="margin">Matt. 9.29.</note> the Deafe beare,<note n="r" place="margin">Mark 2.12.</note> the Lame goe,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Matt. 14.19.</note> and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of people are fedde, with ſome few Loaues and Fiſh.</p>
               <p>If hee will ſhew Mercie,<note n="t" place="margin">Matt. 27.75.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter,</hi> after that he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed Chriſt, ſhall weepe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly,<note n="u" place="margin">Iohn 21.15.</note> and be made Paſtor of his ſheepe.<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 9.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> of a Perſecutor, become an Elect Veſſel and faithful Preacher of the Goſpell; when hee will exalt the humble,<note n="x" place="margin">Sam. 16.11.</note> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhal be taken from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20214:15"/> the ſheepe, and bee made both King<note n="y" place="margin">Sam. 16.13.</note> and Prophet:<note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 41.24.</note> humble <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from the Priſon, and preferred to bee <hi>Pharoes</hi> High Steward:<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 5.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> from the Lions Den, and clothed with Purple.</p>
               <p>When he will execute Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 19.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Sodom</hi> is deuoured with Fire and Brimſtone:<note n="c" place="margin">Matt. 27.45. <hi>Lento gradu ad vindictam ſui procedit Deus, tardita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſupplicij grauitate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſat,</hi> Lipſ. c. 13. lib. 15. &amp; Proper. eleg. 25. lib. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> hanging himſelfe, confeſſed that hee had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed the Innocent:<note n="d" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. Eccleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata, tearing out his bowels, (in the horrour of his Conſcience) cryes out, <hi>Viciſti tandem, Galilaee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When hee will humble the proud, Idolatrous<note n="e" place="margin">Dan. 4.45.</note> 
                  <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezar</hi> ſhall eate graſſe amongſt the beaſts of the field: the baſeſt of GODS Creatures ſhall make hard-hearted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20214:15"/> 
                  <hi>Pharao</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 9.27.</note> ſend for <hi>Moſes,</hi> and confeſſe the true God. Finally, in all his works of Power, Mercy, &amp; Iuſtice, (out of the fierie Furnace)<note n="g" place="margin">Dan. 3.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Shedrach, Meſhach,</hi> &amp; <hi>Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nego,</hi> ſhall proclayme his Glorie.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee, that Gods Workes declare that hee is God, Powerfull, Mercifull, and Iuſt, and that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of theſe Workes are of force eyther (by the leaſt dramme of Grace) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the moſt obſtinate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, to the true knowledge of God, or in Iuſtice to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>ALthough I doe not allow the<note n="h" place="margin">Diuina my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteria credenda, non curiosè ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanda, <hi>Amor. de Diuinis Myſt.</hi>
                  </note> curious
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20214:16"/> ſearching of diuine Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries not reuealed, for admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that in Natures ſchoole, wee are taught to boult out the Truth by Logicall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;<note n="i" place="margin">Neque ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendum de Deo lingua ſufficit, neque ad perci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendum intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus praeualet: magis ergo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficare nos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit Deum quod talis eſt, qui &amp; intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum tranſcendit &amp; cognitionis initium ſuperat, <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> yet in Gods Schoole, it is quite contrarie; hee is the beſt Scholler that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons leaſt, and aſſents moſt, conceiues ſo far as humane frailties will permit, beleeues and admires the reſt, God louing better a credulous heart, then a curious head: yet becauſe your dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God conſiſteth chiefly in the ardent deſire to know God (which is the ſureſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of your loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and of Gods loue towards you) there is a more ſpeciall knowledge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of you, which is,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20214:16"/> that you indeuour your ſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o know him, ſo farre as hee hath reuealed himſelfe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Scriptures called his Word, as proceeding from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Spirit, to bring you to his knowledge: hee hath manifeſted himſelfe in the Scriptures by three ſorts of<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dionyſius</hi> de Diuinis nominibus.</note> names.</p>
               <p>The firſt, are theſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ignifie his Eſſence.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, the perſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Eſſence.</p>
               <p>The third, his eſſentiall Works.</p>
               <p>The names that denote Gods Eſſence, are fiue;</p>
               <p>IEHOVACH, EHEIECH, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ACH, KVRIOS, THEOS.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Non habet ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem aeternita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> aut aliquando finem quae neſcit originem,</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. Mart. Arnob. lib. 1. aduerſ. Gent. Tertul. lib. 2 de Car. Chriſt.</note>
                  <hi>Iehouach,</hi> ſignifieth eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all, being of himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut beginning, and end, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20214:17"/> both in promiſing and performing.</p>
               <p>The ſecond name is <hi>Ehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iech,</hi> of that ſame Roote o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iehoua,</hi> ſignifying, that I am that I am, or I will be that I will bee<note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Eheiech, Aſher, Eheiech.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 21.12, 15, 16, 17.</note>The third name <hi>Iach,</hi> which is Lord, is aſcribed to God, when any notable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, or benefit comes to paſſe, according to his former promiſe.</p>
               <p>The fourth name is<note n="o" place="margin">Iohn 21.7, 12, 15, 16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Ku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios,</hi> vſed oft in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: when it is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen to God, it anſwer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth the <hi>Hebrew</hi> name <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah;</hi> for God is ſo Lord, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he is of himſelfe Lord, and of all others.</p>
               <p>The fift name is <hi>Theos</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20214:17"/> God; It is deriued from, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe<note n="p" place="margin">Deus eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectualis Sphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, cutus centru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vbique, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferentia verò nuſquam, <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> he runnes thorow and compaſſeth all things: when it is properly taken, it ſignifieth the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Eſſence of God, being aboue all things,<note n="q" place="margin">Prouida illa mens, quae coelum hoc quotidiè vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, reuoluit, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ducit, redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, fruges pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, recondit, cauſas &amp; viciſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudines omnes rerum peperit, quas mirantur homines aut quae ſunt, nec quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in hoc grandi Machina geritur, turbatur miſcetur ſpecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum excipio) cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius non cauſa a prima illa cauſa, <hi>Lipſ. lib. 1. de Conſtan. c. 4.</hi>
                  </note> giuing Life and Light to all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, preſeruing and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning them in their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful frame and order, God ſeeing all, and in all places.</p>
               <p>The names that ſignifie the perſons in the Eſſence, are chiefly one.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Sacramentum hoc venera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum, non ſcrutandum quomodo pluralitas ſit in vnitate, &amp; vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas in pluralitate, ſcrutare hoc, temeritas eſt; credere, pietas, noſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> verò, vita aeterna, <hi>Ber.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Elohim,</hi> ſignifieth the mightie Iudges. It is a name of the plurall number, to expreſſe the Trinitie of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the vnity of Eſſence. To this purpoſe, the Holy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20214:18"/> Ghoſt begins the Bible with this plurall Name of God, ioyned with a Verbe of the ſingular Number, as <hi>Elohim bara dij creauit,</hi> the mightie Gods, or all the three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Godhead crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. When you heare of this Name <hi>Elohim,</hi> conſider that in one Diuine Eſſence there are three diſtinct Perſons, &amp; that God is <hi>Iehouach Elohim</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Names that ſignifie Gods Eſſentiall Works, are fiue:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>El, Schaddai, Adonai, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, Abba.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 24.6. Pſal. 24.8.</note> 
                  <hi>El,</hi> is as much to ſay, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſtrong God, ſheweth that God is not onely ſtrong and ſtrength it ſelfe, but tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is hee that giueth al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtrength to his Creatures.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20214:18"/>
               <p>By this Name <hi>Schaddai,</hi> which is Omnipotent, God ſtiled himſelfe vſually to the Patriarks, calling himſelfe <hi>El Schaddai,</hi> the ſtrong God, Almightie: this Name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth onely to God, and to no other Creature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adonai,</hi> my Lord, is found one hundred, thirtie foure times in the old Teſtament: by this Name wee challenge God to be our God, &amp; with <hi>Thomas,</hi> ſay, <hi>Thou art my Lord, and my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Luke 1.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Helion,</hi> which ſignifieth moſt High, was giuen vnto God by <hi>Gabriel,</hi> telling the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that the Child that ſhould be borne of her, ſhould bee the Sonne of the moſt High.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Mar. 14.36. Rom. 8.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Abba,</hi> a Syriake name, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20214:19"/> Father: by it remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, what you receiue from God, proceedeth from a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue, &amp; that you owe him againe filiall obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Sacra Dei no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina quaſi pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora amoris, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiae, &amp; omnipotentiae eius ſunt, <hi>Aug. de Dei Miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. cap. 7.</hi>
                  </note>All theſe ſacred Names of God, are as pledges and remembrances of Gods om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency, and loue towards you, and of your dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</p>
               <p>As the true knowledge of God, is the onely induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the exerciſe of your dutie towards him, ſo the Religious practice of that dutie, is the only rule where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may liue repoſedly, and dye cheerefully.</p>
               <p>In this Exerciſe, I doe commend foure things vnto you, <hi>Heare, Pray, Meditate, and Doc.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20214:19"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>THis hearing, whereof I ſpeak, conſiſteth<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note> in the reading of Gods ſacred word contained in the Bookes of the old and new Teſtament, and hearing it from Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: for the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, giuen by inſpiration of God, and is profitable to teach, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, to correct, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct in righteouſneſſe, that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God may be made perfit in all good workes. The Scriptures are deuided in the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:<note n="b" place="margin">Dicitur vetus testamentum, quia priore, hoc autem nouum, quia poſteriore tempore, reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, Auguſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> ad Bonifac. Reuelationes eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum conſideran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in his nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, non inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutiones, Idem ibidem.</note> the firſt is called old, becauſe it was reuealed in the former time; the other new, becauſe it was reuealed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20214:20"/> in the latter time.</p>
               <p>The difference betwixt the old and new Teſtament is only in certain<note n="c" place="margin">Aliud illi, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud nos, ſed ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie viſibili, quod tamen idem ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificaret virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſpirituali, Aug. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> de ſpirit. &amp; lit. cap. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> accidents, Ceremonies, and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of things, in externall forme, &amp; difference of time, but in ſubſtance all one, and tending to one effect in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and efficacie.</p>
               <p>In the old, the new is<note n="d" place="margin">In veteri no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum latet, &amp; in nouo vetus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet.</note> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured and ſhadowed; in the new, is the declaration and manifeſtation of the old.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Moſes</hi> was the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament reuealed, and the Law giuen, being holy, iuſt, and good,<note n="e" place="margin">Propter vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris hominis noxia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in qua per literam iubentem &amp; minitantem mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimè ſanabatur, dicitur vetus teſtamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum autem, propter nouita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſpiritus, quae hominem nouum ſanat à vitio vetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis, Auguſt. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. cap. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> ſeruing rather to bring vs to the knowledge of our owne inſufficiencie to fulfill the ſame, then for lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon the corrupted ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi> that which they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20214:20"/> were not able to vndergoe.</p>
               <p>The new Teſtament was reuealed by Chriſt, when he was manifeſted in the fleſh, in whom did appeare the righteouſneſſe of God, or the goodnes that comes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God to vs, witneſſed by the Law and Prophets.</p>
               <p>In the Euangelical diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of the Goſpell, is the deliuerance of Gods people, not from an earthly, but from a ſpirituall bondage of ſinne and Satan.</p>
               <p>Heere is a triumph ouer the ſuppreſſed enemie, not <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> but Satan him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Heere is an introduction to poſſeſſe not earthly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> but heauenly <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:20214:21"/>
               <p>Heere is a Law giuen, not in <hi>Sina,</hi> but in <hi>Sion,</hi> not by Angelicall miniſterie, but by the preſence of the Lord himſelfe; not after a fearefull ſort, but with wonderfull lenitie and gentleneſſe; not grauen in ſtonie Tables, but effectually printed in the hearts of the Elect.</p>
               <p>In the old Teſtament was bondage, and feare: in the new, libertie &amp; glad tidings, the miniſtrie not of death; but of life, not a rigorous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acter, but a mercifull Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; not the ſacraments of Circumciſion, and the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, (the adminiſtration whereof was bloudie) but Baptiſme, &amp; the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, both <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudie.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20214:21"/>
               <p>In the new Teſtament is a Prieſthood, not Aaroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, not externall, not tyed to any one Nation &amp; Tribe, but ſpirituall, and common to all the faithfull through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world.</p>
               <p>In it is a Sacrifice, and that bloudie, but not of Beaſts, but the ſweet ſmelling Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the precious body and bloud of our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus; not i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terated, but finiſhed once for all vpon the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>In the new Teſtament are Ceremonies few and eaſie, to wit, the Word, Sacraments, and Prayers.</p>
               <p>(In one word) in the old Teſtament were figures, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and promiſes: in the new, the fulfilling &amp; accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20214:22"/> of them all: this new Couenant of Grace ſhal continue to the worlds end, and ſhall giue place to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but to the eternall fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
               <p>Heereby the excellencie of the new Teſtament is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and that both the old and new, differing in acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and circumſtances, are in ſubſtance &amp; truth all one, and that the one is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the other, making vp an abſolute body<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <p>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credimus, nihil deſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus vltra cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</p>
                     <p>Hoc enim priùs credimus, non eſſe quod vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra credere debemus, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tull. lib. de praeſcript. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ret.</p>
                     <p>Scrut. mini Scripturas. <hi>Ioh. 5.39.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning perfit ſufficiencie to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and whereto we muſt neither adde nor diminiſh, neither ſeeke for Chriſt and ſaluation elſewhere; for this cauſe we are commanded to ſearch the Scriptures.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20214:22"/>
               <p>Therefore wouldeſt thou know what ſinne is, and the puniſhment thereof by the Law?<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 50. Exod. 90. Leuit. 29. Numb. 36. Deut. 39.</note> The fiue Bookes of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall teach thee the Hiſtoricall partes of theſe:<note n="b" place="margin">Ioſua 29. Iudges 21.1. 2. Sam. 55.1. 2. Kings 97.1. 2. Chron. 65. Ezra. 10. Nehem. 13. Eſter 10. Iob 42.</note> the Books of the Prophets, Prouerbs of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> will let you ſee the Reward of the Godly, and puniſhment of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and furniſh you with a rich Store-houſe of Golden ſentences, and diuine Morall Precepts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 150. Prouerb. 31. Eccleſ. 12. Eſai. 66. Iere. 2.52. Lam. 5. Eze. 48. Daniel 11. Hoſ. 14. Ioel 3. Amos 9. Obe. 1. Ionah. 4. Micah. 5. Nahum. 3. Abacu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k. 3. Zephania 3. Hagaij 2. Zecha. 14. Mal. 4.</note>The Kingly Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhall plentifully admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto you Heauenly Phyſicke for all Spirituall diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 28. Mar. 16. Lu. 24. Ioh. 21.</note>The 4. Euangeliſts ſhall teach you the Life, Doctrine, and Death of our Sauiour.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:20214:23"/>
               <p>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 28.</note>The Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſhall acquaint you with the practice of CHRISTS Doctrine in the Primitiue Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 16.1. 2. Corin. 2.9. Galat. 6. Epheſ. 6. Philip. 4. Col. 4.1. 2. Theſ. 8.1. 2. Tim. 10. Tit. 3. Phile. 1. Heb. 13. Iames 5.1. 2. Peter 8.1. 2. Iohn 5. Iude 1. Reuel. 22.</note>The Epiſtles of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſhall traine you vp particularly in Chriſt his Schoole.</p>
               <p>Make vſe of the reſt of the Bookes called<note n="*" place="margin">3. Eſdras 4. Eſdras Tob. Iudith. Eſter. Wiſdome. Eccleſ. Bar. The Song of the three Children. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſanna. The Hiſtorie of Bell and the Dragon. The Prayer of Manaſtes. 1. Mac. 2. Mac.</note> Apocrypha, ſo far as they agree with the Scripture, and no further.</p>
               <p>Read the Scriptures with a ſanctified and chaſt heart: for vnleſſe they be read by the inſpiration of GODS Spirit, (by the which they were written) with humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and deſire to know, they remaine as a dead letter in the efficacie thereof (as I did aduiſe you before.) Admire
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20214:23"/> reuerently ſuch obſcure pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as by your weake capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city you cannot vnderſtand, neuer going further in the curious ſearch of diuine My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, then either by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring ſome other place of Scripture, or by conference with ſome learned Diuine you may bee informed: for as the Scriptures haue in them that height and depth to exerciſe the Learned: ſo haue they that eaſineſſe and plaineneſſe, that the ſimple maybe comforted &amp; taught; they are that admirable Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer (both ſhallow &amp; deepe) wherein as the Lambe may wade, the Elephant may ſwimme; and it is only the dulneſſe of our capacitie that makes them hard to vs,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20214:24"/> and the Vale of our hearts that cannot bee remooued, except by him that hath the Key of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that opens where no man ſhuts, and ſhuts where no man opens.</p>
               <p>Delight moſt in ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, as ſerue beſt for your inſtruction in your owne calling: for many men are too buſie in other mens callings,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fides per audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> Rom. 10.17. 1. Sam. 2.30. Eſay 28.14. 2. Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> and neglecters of their owne.</p>
               <p>The hearing of Gods Word by the Scriptures, and by Paſtors, &amp; the practice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will giue you knowledge, worke Holineſſe in you, breake downe your naturall corruptions, and fill you with ſtrength againſt all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20214:24"/>
               <head>SECT. IIII.</head>
               <p>PRayer, is a ſimple, vnfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, humble, and ardent opening of the heart before God, wherein we either aske things needful for our ſelues and others, or giue thanks for benefits receiued: it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publique in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the faithfull, or priuat, when we pray alone.</p>
               <p>There be foure chiefe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ought to induce vs to Prayer: firſt, the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God: ſecondly, our ſinnes, which driue vs of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie to God for life, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, and help. Thirdly, our weake nature, (being of it ſelfe vnable to ſubſiſt) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth Prayer to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20214:25"/> it, as a houſe pillars to vphold it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, the ſubtiltie of the enemy (who euer attendeth to ouerthrow vs, euen in thoſe things we thinke to be beſt done) ought to ſturre vs vp vehemently to Prayer.</p>
               <p>The excellencie of Prayer is manifeſt by the dignitie of the Commander, and the admirable effects that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it. The Commander is God, Lord of Heauen and earth, of our life, and death, the Fountain of all goodnes, the effects thereof are ſuch, that (Prayer proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a faithfull ſoule, and ſquared by Gods Word) will ſtay the Sunne to end our victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the falling of the raine from heauen, and at our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20214:25"/> againe, ſend down plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of it to increaſe the fruits of the earth for our comfort, it will pierce the heauens for mercie, and pardon for our ſinnes, ſtay the wrath of God againſt vs for the ſame, and obtaine whatſoeuer good thing is needful for vs in this life, or in the life to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Oratione ſedulo cura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum eſt, ne intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one aliqua re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentè facta, rur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus languaſcere incipiat anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> alacritas,</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard. de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſ. relig. Mat. 7.7. Luke 18.1. Rom. 12.12. Epheſ 6.18. Col. 4.2. 1. Tim. 2.8.</note> Let your Prayers bee daily, without intermiſſion: for deuotion that is defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon conceit of preſent vnfitneſſe or worldly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, at laſt groweth irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and altogether neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: ſuffer not your heart to entertayne the leaſt thought of lothneſſe in the taske of deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly breake thorow ſuch motions, with a deepe check to your ſelfe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20214:26"/> for your backwardneſſe. And becauſe holineſſe doth not (like<note n="a" place="margin">Ionah 3.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Ionas</hi> Gourd) grow vp in a day, it is better to goe on ſafe and ſure, then for an haſtie fit, (as many doe) run out of winde, and then ſtand ſtill. Goe to Prayer, as you would goe to the water to ſwimme; goe not hot in, but take a time to coole your ſelfe by Meditation,<note n="b" place="margin">Homo in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem, Deus in praecordia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatur, <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> feeling that your words touch the very depth of your Soule.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Animaduerto Deum, non tam adorantium pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus, quàm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentia, &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitate laetari, gratiorem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eum qui delubris eius puram castam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mentem, quàm qui meditatum carmen intulerit exiſtimare, <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ l. b. 3. Prou. 30.12.</hi>
                  </note> Frame not your Prayers (as ſome hypocritically do) according to the fantaſies of your owne braine, neither (as others ſuperſtitiouſly) thinke to mooue God by iterations and babbling, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (with the proud <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe</hi>) preſuming vpon your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20214:26"/> owne worth, but (like vnto that poore <hi>Publican</hi>) hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, with all reuerence,<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod. 3.5.</hi> Ad beatitudinem rectè conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, omnia fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gienda ſunt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia, <hi>Auguſt. de Ciuit. Dei.</hi>
                  </note> (throwing off the ſhooes of your corrupt affections) proſtrate your ſelfe at the footſtoole of Gods Throne of Grace, demanding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is repugnant to his will (leſt you tempt him)<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 6.8.</note> who out of his inſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Wiſdome knoweth beſt what is good for you.</p>
               <p>In your Prayers, haue a ſpeciall care, that you keepe euer as a patterne before you, that Prayer<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 6.9.</note> ſet downe by the Mercy-Maſter Chriſt Ieſus, called the Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. It is the pure Fountaine, from whence the Riuers of Life muſt flow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20214:27"/>
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>MEditation is a carefull conſideration or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout calling to mind, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination both of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and temporall eſtate, by a ſerious contemplation of Gods goodnes towards vs, what dutie he requireth of vs towards him, and for his ſake to our neighbour, and how wee haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſame, what reward remaineth for the godly, and puniſhment for the wicked, that wee haue an account to render not onely of euery miſ-ſpent day, but of euery idle word, in what eſtate, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall or temporall, we ſtand for the preſent.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20214:27"/>
               <p>This holy Meditation ſtirreth vs vp to a thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for Gods goodnes, to ſorrow, and repentance, for our by-paſt offences, and to a ſetled reſolution of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our liues in time to come.<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal 49.3. <hi>Contemplante animo, nihil al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius ſublimiuſue eſſe poteſt,</hi> Ciel. Rhod. l. 25. c. 12</note> Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the moſt ſoueraigne cure of the ſoule: in it keepe this courſe, retyre your ſelf euery day (at ſome fit time) to your<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 6.6.</note> chamber, Studie, Field, or ſome ſecret place, and hauing prayed to God for a recollected minde, enter into a conſideration of your ſinfull eſtate,<note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.28.</note> examine your ſelf, take notice of your paſſions, diſpoſition and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, whereby you may come to the knowledge of your ſelfe; and by calling for helpe from God, reſolue
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20214:28"/>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Fortior eſt qui ſe, quàm qui fortiſſima vincit moenia, <hi>Amb.</hi>
                  </note> to conquer your ſelfe as a walled Citie.</p>
               <p>Call to minde, if any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe hath paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you and<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 3.10. Mat. 5.22.</note> your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or any other; and if you remember any rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or the leaſt cole of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie or Malice, (lurking vnder the Aſhes of your peruerſe nature) wipe away and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh them, by not<note n="m" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.26. Mat. 6.14, 15.</note> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Sunne goe downe vpon your wrath: for he that craueth pardon, and will not forgiue, is like vnto him that breaketh downe a Bridge, that he muſt paſſe ouer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>In your Meditation, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire diligently<note n="n" place="margin">Non poteſt praeſentem diem rectè viuere, qui ſe non eum quaſi vltimum victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſſe cogitat, <hi>Aug. de Mort.</hi>
                  </note> after the day of your death, by ſetting it before your eyes, by exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20214:28"/> your ſelfe whether you bee prepared, and<note n="o" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.54</note> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and by incouraging your cowardly ſoule, to looke Death in the face, flying e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in this poynt, to thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour for helpe.</p>
               <p>Conclude thy meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by thinking vpon thy worldly eſtate: if it proſper, lay vp humility in thy heart. If poore,<note n="p" place="margin">Pſalme 119.</note> pray for ſupply, and thinke vpon ſome law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and honeſt meanes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>THe fourth and moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie part (belonging to a Chriſtian) is<note n="q" place="margin">Mat 7.21. Pſal. 103.18.</note> doing (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the life of all) for it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (and vſuall to Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites)<note n="r" place="margin">Eſay 58.2.</note> to be religious in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20214:29"/> Ceremonies, ioyne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (as <hi>indiuidui Comites</hi>) the liuely<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 2.22.</note> Faith of <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Iam. 2.13, 14, 16, 17, 26.</note> with S. <hi>Iames,</hi> good Works: Faith without Works, makes but a Carnall Goſpeller, and Workes without Faith, a Phariſaicall Hypocrite.</p>
               <p>Euer in doing, beware of doing againſt thy<note n="u" place="margin">Qui conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae curam obijci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, nec Deum nec homines re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerentur: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia vna ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in nobis ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis accuſator, teſtis, Iudex, Tortor, &amp; Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, <hi>Bernard.</hi>
                  </note> Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for the treaſure of a good Conſcience, is the beſt ſtore you can prouide for a quiet life here, and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hereafter, when a dram of it ſhall ſerue you to better vſe, then innumerable milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gold.</p>
               <p>Omit neither time, place, nor perſon, if thou canſt doe good:<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 25.35, 41. Eſay 58 7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.18. Prou. 19.17.</note> remember Chriſts laſt Iudgement, wherein he ſheweth that the beſt good
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20214:29"/> in the World is Compaſſion, Almes, and comforting in Diſtreſſe, as in Sickneſſe, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, Impriſonment, or Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; for although God accepteth of good thoughts, yet towards man, they are little better then good dreames: exerciſe therefore thy charitable offices, (as Gods Steward) vpon thy Brethren. Remember, it is now the time,<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Viue memor qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſis aeui bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis. Mors ſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in Ianuis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenibus inſidijs,</hi> Senec. de Mort. Pſal. 90.16. Iam. 4.14. Pſal. 103.15.</note> thy life is ſhort, thy dayes euill,<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> thy death certaine,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 25.19.</note> thy account moſt certayne, thy ioyes vnſpeakeable, if thou doe well: for this cauſe labour to husband the Talent that God hath put into thy hands, that thou maiſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne thy ſoule better then thou didſt receiue it. If that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20214:30"/> ſeruant was<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 25.30.</note> condemned as ill, that did giue his Maſter no more but his owne, what ſhall become of him that robs God of his owne?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>SLoth<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou. 6.6 v. 15.</hi> Ignauia turma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n nos ruens, eligi facilis plana ad eam, &amp; expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita eſt via, at virtutem ſudore dij obuallarunt, <hi>Zenoph. de dict. Soc.</hi>
                  </note> is the Mother of many euils, and the chiefe corrupter of Chriſtian due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; baniſh it by diligence, in all theſe former exerciſes, neyther<note n="n" place="margin">Non delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenti, ſed poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti, &amp; pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarelinqucati condonat Deus, <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> deferring Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for thy by-paſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects, neyther amendment of thy former life.<note n="o" place="margin">Quis eſt ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcens, cui explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum ſit, ſe ad vesperum eſſe victurum? <hi>Cic. de Sen.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Baſil.</hi> In denu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciata ſorte rapimur, <hi>Fuſc. Suaſor. 2.</hi>
                  </note> Who knoweth, but Death may ſhut vp thy breath, at an vnprouided time? Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Amendment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the free Gifts of God, the Tree of Faith (watered
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20214:30"/> by Gods Grace) onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth (not common in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie mans Garden:) this Tree muſt be planted in the ſpring of thy Youth, and not in the Froſty Winter, when the day ſhall come, wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure. It muſt bee daily laboured, hedged, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from the annoya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, Caterpillers, and choking Weedes of the World; by this meanes it ſhall produce plentifull ſtore of Fruit in thy life, and at thy Death prepare thee, (with old <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> in the peace of a good Conſcience) to ſay,<note n="p" place="margin">Luke 2.27.</note> Lord, <hi>now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace, for mine eyes haue ſeene my Saluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I haue ſhortly poynted at
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20214:31"/> Gods wonderfull Workes, of Power, Mercie, and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, at thoſe Names, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by chiefely hee hath reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelfe in his Word; and at the duties that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in his ſeruice.</p>
               <p>That I may come (with the like breuitie) to thoſe things that may bring you to the knowledge of your ſelfe, I will conclude this firſt part, ſubioyning this enſuing Prayer, which by GODS Grace will inable you to attayne to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that is craued of you, in your Chriſtian calling.</p>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:20214:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.17.</note>ALmightie and<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 15.11.</note> glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, full of incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Power &amp; Maieſtie,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> whoſe glory the heauen (of heauens) is not able to containe, thou that art the ſtrong God that<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 12.13.</note> forgiuest offences, and paſſeſt by iniquities,<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 10.17.</note> that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareſt the heart of the poore, and openeſt thine eare to heare their praiers:<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 17.</note> Incline, O Lord, thine eares, and heare me: open<note n="i" place="margin">Dan. 9.5.</note> thine eyes, and ſee a poore and wretched ſinner; O Lord,<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 5.21.</note> I haue done excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wickedly in thy ſight: I doe acknowledge and confeſſe it, and doe humbly proſtrate my ſelfe at the<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 7.49.</note> foote-ſtoole of thy Throne of Grace for pardon,<note n="m" place="margin">Ierem. 31.3, 4.</note> thou haſt promiſed, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the riches of thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20214:32"/> to forgiue my offences, yea, more to ſhew the ſtabilitie of thy Councell, thou haſt tyed thy ſelfe by an<note n="n" place="margin">Luke 1.73.</note> oath thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſealed the Couenant thereof with the<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 27.57.</note> bloud of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate Lambe, thy Sonne, the Lord Ieſus, at his death vpon the Croſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Exod. 33.19.</note>Regard, O Lord, thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and free Mercie, the Oath of thy Holineſſe, the Words of thy owne Mouth: let mee feele the accompliſhment thereof in my ſoule:<note n="q" place="margin">Ierem. 31.33, 34.</note> write it in my heart by thy Spirit, and ſeale it in my Conſcience by the powerfull ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of that ſame bloud there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that it may<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 51.2, 7.</note> waſh away all my ſinnes and tranſgreſſsions;<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 27.60.</note> burie them in Chriſts buriall, that they may neuer riſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, to<note n="t" place="margin">Dan. 9.7.</note> ſhame me in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20214:32"/> this life,<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 25.91.</note> neither to condemne me in the life to come; Create in mee, O God, that peace of Conſcience that paſſeth all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding:<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> Thy free pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in Ieſus Christ, make me bold to come before thee; thou art the very Truth, and able to performe; and as in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie I craue this, according to thy<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 33.19.</note> promiſe: ſo by the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe I doe earneſtly begge thy<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal.</note> grace, that I may hereafter lead a more holy and godly life; ſanctifie my ſoule by the ſame grace, that it may be a fit<note n="c" place="margin">Cor. 6.19.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle for thy holy Spirit; and giue command<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 18.10. Act. 12.7. Pſal. 39.7.</note> to thy good Angels, to attend both my ſoule and bodie, that in neither of them I make defection from ſo gracious a God;<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal.</note> remooue all occaſions that may ſtay mee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20214:33"/> in this good courſe, and grant vnto me ſuch neceſſaries, as may aduance mee in thy ſeruice.<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 28.20.</note> Grant vnto mee Competent meanes, that I may neither bee puffed vp with deceitfull pride, neither depreſſed with extreme pouertie;<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 13.3.</note> Giue me grace to vſe thoſe meanes to thy glorie, the ſupply of thoſe things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which I am not able to ſerue thee,<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 13.3.</note> and to the helpe of my diſtreſſed Brethren.<note n="k" place="margin">1. Reg. 8.30.</note> Looke downe from heauen in Mercie vpon<note n="l" place="margin">Can. 2.6.</note> thy whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church &amp; euery Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof diſperſed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World; bee with them (O Lord) and keepe thoſe that<note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 17.9. Deut. 32.3.</note> are thine, vnder the Wings of thy Mercie;<note n="n" place="margin">Math. 11.28</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member likewiſe all diſtreſſed perſons of this Church;<note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 13.3.</note> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20214:33"/> it bee griefe of body or minde:) mitigate ſo their paines, and comfort their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Conſciences, that either in<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> life or<note n="q" place="margin">Act. 7.56.</note> death they may haue a ioyfull deliuerance.</p>
                  <p>Let thy mercifull bountie be extended vpon all thoſe of this Church in great Britaine, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and ſpecially<note n="ſ" place="margin">Tim. 2.1.2.</note> vpon our gracious and dread Soueraigne King <hi>Iames,</hi> as it hath pleaſed thee to grant vnto him<note n="t" place="margin">Chro. 1.12. 1. Reg. 3.12.</note> (<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>-like) Wiſedome from heauen, in the true knowledge of thee, the peaceable gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy people, and<note n="u" place="margin">1. Reg. 2.28.</note> true adminiſtration of Iuſtice: ſo by the like fauour preſerue him from all dangers of ſoule and bodie,<note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 27.</note> and after <hi>Methuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> age, crowne him with an euerlaſting Crowne of Glorie.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20214:34"/> Bleſſe<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 72.1.</note> that hopefull Prince <hi>Charles</hi> (next vnto his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)<note n="z" place="margin">1. Eſ. 17.19.</note> the very life of our hopes, and the reſt of that Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Iſſue: remember (O Lord) thy promiſe made to <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; his ſeede for euer, and<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 18.50. Math. 24.29.</note> ſo long as the Sunne giues light to the World, let vs neuer want one of that Royall Line to ſway the Scepter ouer vs:<note n="b" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.2. Heb. 13.18.</note> grant grace vnto the Lords of his Maieſties moſt honourable Councell, and to all inferior Magiſtrates ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſtical or Ciuil,<note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 18.21.</note> that they may with a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; courage diſcharge their ſeuerall callings.</p>
                  <p>Finally, I doe not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate thy Maieſties protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this day, but<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 38.22, 71, 17.</note> all the daies of my life, and in<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note> the ende thereof, that I being garded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20214:34"/> the defence of thy (All-ſheelding) Mercie, may in the end participate of<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> thoſe inſpeakeable ioyes prepared for all them that put their truſt in thee.<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 9.9.26.12.32.10.</note> Now, yeelding all humble and heartie thankes for all thy benefits from time to time, and eſpecially at this time, I conclude my<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 6.5.</note> imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Prayers with the patterne of all Prayers, and<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 5.9.</note> which the Lord IESVS hath taught, ſaying, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:20214:35"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p>NExt vnto the knowledge of God &amp; your duty to him (hauing the approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a good<note n="p" place="margin">Nil iuuat bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num nomen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamante con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia, <hi>Caſſ.</hi>
                  </note> Conſcience) ſeeke for a good reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among men, not by cloſe carriage or concealing your faults, but by eſchewing all thoſe vices that may iuſtly deſerue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch: for it is hard to doe good, except a man bee thought good: therefore wiſely<note n="*" place="margin">Palpebrae praecedunt greſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, cum opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem conſilia rectè praeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niunt. Qui enim negligit conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando praeuidere quod facit, greſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus tendit, ſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos claudit, pergendo iter con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cit, ſed prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidendo ſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metipſi, non an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedit; atque idcirco citius corruit, quoniam vbi pedem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ponere debet, per conſilij pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pebram non at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendit, <hi>Greg. Rom. de paſt. par. 3. c. 1.</hi>
                  </note> foreſee and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that a good name and reputation (being the <hi>Manna</hi> &amp; <hi>Nepenthe</hi> of generous Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits) is ſo delicate, that the leaſt exceſſe doth blemiſh, an vniuſt action doth diſhonor it, an act of in diſcretion, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, or idleneſſe, defaceth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20214:35"/> it, and a ſiniſter ſucceſſe ruins it: and as Glaſſe crackt is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broken, ſo is a Mans good name once iuſtly tainted.</p>
               <p>Obſerue dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Quid prauius? quid malignius? quidue aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſario noſtro ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quius? qui po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit in Coelo bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, in Paradiſo fraudem, odium inter primos fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres &amp; in omni noſtro opere, zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zania ſeminá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, in comeſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione poſuit gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam, in genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione luxuriam, in exercitatione ignauiam, in conuerſatione inuidiam, in gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernatione aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritiam, in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione iram, in dominatione ſuperbiam: in corde poſuit cogitationes malas, in or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones falſas, in membris operationes iniquas, in vigilando mouet ad praua opera, in dormiendo ad ſomnia turpia, lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos mouet ad diſſolutionem, triſtes ad desperationem, &amp; vt breuius loquar, omnia mala ſunt ipſius prauitate commiſſa, <hi>Aug. deſcribens conatus Diab.</hi>
                  </note> Arch-Enemie to Man, the World &amp; your own corrupt affections (with whom you are to enter Combat) are 3. da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous enemies, &amp; (ſo long as breath entertaynes your Earthly Manſion) ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer leaue to aſſault you: the firſt is Cruell, Diligent, and Trecherous: the ſecond, falſe and inconſtant (beeing rightly called<note n="*" place="margin">Nihil tam contrarium rationi, &amp; conſtantiae, quàm mundi inconſtantia, <hi>Cic. lib. 2. de Diuin.</hi> Quod ego fui ad tracimenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tu hodie ad cannas es: verba <hi>Hannib. ad Scip.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mundus, à mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendo,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:20214:36"/> becauſe it is in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall motion without any ſtabilitie) &amp; the third (being a<note n="a" place="margin">Sua domeſtica vitia quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giat, nam aliena non nocebunt, <hi>Guig. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th. Medit. cap. 2.</hi>
                  </note> Domeſtical Enemie, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther troopes of inmate foes) will haue their hands in the Diſh with you, and yet <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>-like) euer readie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray you with a kiſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p>HAue a ſpecial care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſeuen chiefe Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions that ſhall be ſent out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you.</p>
               <p>Firſt,<note n="b" place="margin">Superbia, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. eſt vitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muliebre ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia, &amp; arguit oris duritiem, ac ſenſus qualis ineſt, <hi>Lapidi. Text.</hi>
                  </note> Pride ſhall indeuor to make you, with <hi>Lucifer,</hi> be thruſt out of Heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Inuidia, Gen. <hi>3.1.</hi> Squalida vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereas mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans foemina car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dolent oculi, quaeque ſuum cor edit; quam macies &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llor habent; ſpinoſa<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> geſtat tela manu; talis pingitur inuidia</note> Enuie, with that olde Serpent, ſhall perſwade you to eat the forbidden fruit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Ira, Gen <hi>4.8.</hi> Irae affectus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus poſitus eſt in impetu doloris, armorum ſanguinis minimè humana feruens cupiditate, <hi>Sen. de Ira. Pro. 15.19.</hi>
                  </note> Wrath ſhall ſtirre you
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20214:36"/> vp to kill innocent <hi>Abel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Segnities ſpecies rectè ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata cucullo; Non ſe non alios, vtilitate iuvat.</note> Sloth, that lazie Slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, ſhall make your Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard bee ouergrowne with Thornes and Nettles.</p>
               <p>Neuer-ſatisfied<note n="f" place="margin">Auaritia, <hi>2. Reg. 21.1. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhua <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.2.</hi> Auarus tam fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itur quod non habet, quàm quod habet.</note> Couet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall moue you to deſire <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard, &amp; with <hi>Achan,</hi> value a Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Garment, a few Shekels of Siluer, and a Wedge of Gold, at an higher price then thy owne, or the bloud of thy whole Family.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, (without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant reſiſtance)<note n="g" place="margin">Ebrietas, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 9 33</hi> per temu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neſciens, miſcet libidine inceſtum; &amp; quem Sodoma non vicit, vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na, <hi>Cle. Alex. l. 2. c. 19.</hi>
                  </note> Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is able to make thee commit Inceſt with thy owne Daughters.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, (ſeeming ſweete poyſoned)<note n="h" place="margin">Luxuria, <hi>2.</hi> Sam. <hi>11.4, 17.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le ſatae Circes tam magna po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ertur, verterit, vt mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tos in noua mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra viros, <hi>Iune.</hi>
                  </note> Lecherie ſhall attempt to cauſe <hi>Vriah</hi> to be placed in the front of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20214:37"/> Battaile, that thou maiſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy <hi>Berſhebah.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <p>YOu ſee then the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of your Enemies, againſt whoſe aſſaults, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther multitude can reſiſt, neyther Armie withſtand, but the reſolutions of a<note n="i" place="margin">Sapiens om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium horarum hon o eſt. <hi>Iuue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Sat. 10.</hi> Quid illa virtus quae prudentia dicitur, nonne tota vigilantia ſua, bona diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit à malis, vt in illis appeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis, ipſiſque vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis nullus error obrepat? <hi>Aug. de Ciuit. Dei, l. 10. c 4.</hi>
                  </note> wiſeman, grounded vpon the feare of his Maker, that this Armour may ſerue you for<note n="k" place="margin">Alia in alijs vitia principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum obtinent, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rannidem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercent; Ideo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> oportet vnum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quemque no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum, ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qualitatem belli quo principaliter infeſtatur pugnam arripere, <hi>Caſſ. colla. 6. c 27.</hi> Quamuis res bellicae caecos habea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euentus, tu tamen dimicandi voluntatem pro victoriae pignore tene, <hi>Nazian. Paneg. Conſtant.</hi>
                  </note> vndertaking the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, (maintayning it with courage) and making your retrait (although by death) with the reputation of a wiſe and valorous Souldier; ſquare all your Actions by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20214:37"/> the Rules of Vertue and Reaſon; and continue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the ſame, in things contrarie and diuerſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out change of your conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and vertue. For as Gold, wrought into diuers faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and transformed into ſundrie kind of Ornaments, remains ſtill the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; ſo a Wiſeman conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth always the ſame, what ſoeuer hapneth; he is fit for all chances; he is Gouernor of the bad, Intertayner of the good, he exerciſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo, that hee ſheweth his vertue aſwell in<note n="l" place="margin">Gubernator in tempeſtate dignoſcitur, miles in acie pro atur, &amp; <hi>Caeſari</hi> ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in aduerſis quam in prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris maior animus fuit, <hi>Val. Max.</hi>
                  </note> aduerſe as proſperous affaires; hee will ſhew it in Wealth, in Pouertie, in his Countrie, in Baniſhment, when hee is a Commander, if not a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20214:38"/> Souldier, in health, if not in ſickneſſe, or in death it<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epaminon das</hi> cum Leuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum &amp; manti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neam, ſecundis praelijs contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet; haſta tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectus, ſanguine &amp; ſpiritu defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens, recreare ſe conantem primum an cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peus ſuus ſaluus eſſet, deinde an hoſtes penitus fuſi orent, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ogauit, quae cum ex an mi ſententia compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, Non finis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit comilito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vitae meae, ſed meli <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; altius initium aduenit, nunc enim veſter dux <hi>Epaminondas</hi> naſcitur, quia ſic monitur, <hi>Valerius Maximus.</hi>
                  </note> ſelfe; hee can ſubdue all euils whatſoeuer; hauing his chiefe pleaſures in thoſe things that are neyther ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to time, or corruption:<note n="n" place="margin">Nunquam temeritas cum conſilio comm ſcetur, nec ad conſilium caſus admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur, <hi>Cic. pro Mar.</hi> Maximus bellum ſic inſtruxit, vt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet omnium circumſpectus quae contra cum poterant exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitari, <hi>Treb. Pol. in Gall.</hi>
                  </note> his valour is neuer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iudgement, nor his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes without conduct; he hath Iuſtice in his armes, Wiſdome in his counſels, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lancie and Fidelitie in his executions, Sufferance in paine, &amp; patience at all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; he chuſeth not friends by their greatneſſe, neyther is hee luxurious after new acquaintance; he maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20214:38"/> the ſtrength of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, not by Delicacies, but by Temperance, and his minde by giuing it preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence ouer his bodie, he is Seruant of Vertue, and Friend of the moſt High; his reſolutions are<note n="o" place="margin">Multa nouit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, Felis v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num magnum, <hi>ex Fab. Aeſop.</hi> Nihil eſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta virtute quod (mortali animo &amp; manu) immortale que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri poteſt, <hi>V. Max.</hi>
                  </note> few and well ſettled; wandring re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions (oft-times ending in confuſion) are none of his; hee is thus, and will bee thus. Clouds flye ouer the Sunne, Darkneſſe followeth Light, and Light Darkneſſe; nothing vnder Heauen is at one<note n="p" place="margin">Credamꝰ ſextio monſtranti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter pulcherrimum, et clamanti, Hâc i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur ad aſtra, <hi>Sen. Epiſt. 72.</hi>
                  </note> ſtay and permanent, but the reſolutions of a wiſe and vertuous minde, Vertue beeing a proportion and vprightneſſe of minde in poynts agreeable to reaſon, making the Poſſeſſours hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20214:39"/> becauſe whatſoeuer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens vnto them, Vertue turnes it into good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI.</head>
               <p>AS doing good is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not doing euil, ſo (for the better exerciſing your ſelfe in the practice of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues) I doe rather recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto you, honeſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie, then a<note n="ſ" place="margin">Omnia mala nobis ſolitudo perſuadet, <hi>Cen. Epiſt. 25.</hi> Solitudo eſt, quae etiam virum fortem fortiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me praecipitat, in reatum, <hi>Petr. Bleſ. Epiſt. 9. Crates,</hi> cum vid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſet adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem, ſolùm ambulantem, interrogauit quid illic face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret? Mecum, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, loquor. Caue, inquit <hi>Crates,</hi> rogo, vt diligenter atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das ne cum homine malo loquaris, <hi>Sen.</hi> Si de fatuis, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio tibi neceſſaria eſt: ſi de prudentibus, tu congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni, <hi>Ber. Epiſt. 115.</hi>
                  </note> Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and Heremitiſh life; but in the choyce of your companie, great care is to be had,<note n="t" place="margin">Res eſt contagioſa ſocietas mala, &amp; ſicut grex totus, vnius ſcabie cadit, &amp; porrigine porci, vua<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conspectu liuore ducit ab vua, <hi>Iuuenal.</hi> Valetudinem fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsimam laedit aer grauis, &amp; aura peſtilens; Ita mentem optimam conuerſatio cum malis.</note> that you conuerſe with none, but ſuch whoſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20214:39"/> diſpoſition is honeſt, and vertuous; affect not multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of friends, (remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that ancient ſaying, He that hath many Friends, hath eaten too much Salt at Meales) but (after good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice) ſettle your friendſhip with ſuch, who reuerence<note n="x" place="margin">Multi non amico ſed amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia caruerunt, hoc non poteſt accidere, cum amicos, in ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem honeſta cupiendi par trahit voluntas, <hi>Sen. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. 6.</hi> Verae amicitiae cauſa vnica, virtus, <hi>Plut.</hi>
                  </note> friendſhip, as the habit of a continued loue, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a true vertuous diſpoſition; vniting two ſoules in one will, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the conuerſing of friends, their mutuall parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating, eyther priuate ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, or conceyued plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, to bee the true end of friendſhip; for this cauſe did <hi>Theſeus</hi> chooſe <hi>Perithous, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restes, Pilades.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let your friend be ſuch,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20214:40"/> who accounteth beauty but a blaze, wealth a fickle fauor of Fortune; but friendſhip to be the precious chayne of humane ſocietie, and of ſuch Vertue, that neyther<note n="x" place="margin">Tales nobis amicos quaerere dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, qui extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n periculo, veletiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ost mortem veri a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici permanca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>Val. Max.</hi>
                  </note> time nor fortune can corrupt.</p>
               <p>In friendſhip abandon (as an infectiue poyſon) ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iealouſie, and<note n="y" place="margin">Cum amico omnes cogitatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, omnes curas miſce, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n.</hi> Quibus eſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nis amor, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non neceſſe eſt, hos ipſos cum voluptate, ſe mutuo aspicere, beneuole collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui, fidem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuam habere? <hi>Xen in conui.</hi>
                  </note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate not onely your minde, but your moſt waightie affaires to your friend; and if ſometime you keepe vp any thing from him, let it be to auoid ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of facilitie.</p>
               <p>Vſe not your friends like Sutes of Apparrell, in wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them thred-bare, and then call for new, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thou oweſt him foure dueties;<note n="z" place="margin">Exiſtimabam quo enim magis in rebus aduerſis iuuiſſem, tantô fore mihi in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperis amiciorem <hi>Xen Paeda. l 7.</hi> Sincerae fidei a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici praecipue in aduerſis co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur. <hi>V. Max.</hi>
                  </note> with thy
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20214:40"/> purſe, with thy perſon, with thy comfort, and counſell.</p>
               <p>In true friendſhip pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſpecially required: for there is no man that hath not ſomewhat to bee miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſhall not iuſtly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſomething in you; if your friends faults bee few, ſwallow and digeſt them, if many, ſmother them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but louingly notifie them to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Let nothing but death &amp; villainie diuorce you from your friend, but ſtill follow him ſo farre as is eyther poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible or honeſt, and then<note n="a" place="margin">Affabilitas &amp; comitas res ſunt nullius im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendij, amicitias tamen multas conglutinant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitae, diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uunt praetermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, <hi>Cic.</hi>
                  </note> leaue him with ſorrow.</p>
               <p>In your geſture and words be<note n="a" place="margin">Affabilitas &amp; comitas res ſunt nullius im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendij, amicitias tamen multas conglutinant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitae, diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uunt praetermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, <hi>Cic.</hi>
                  </note> courteous to all men, by this means you ſhal procure loue, and keep friendſhip faſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:20214:41"/>
               <head>SECT. XII.</head>
               <p>FOr the better mayntay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this friendſhip, &amp; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to that perfection, that is demanded in the true vſe of ſocietie; you muſt haue diligent care<note n="b" place="margin">Neſcit poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda loqui, qui proferenda, ſuo tradidit exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, <hi>Quintilian.</hi>
                  </note> what you ſpeak, and how you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. I doe confeſſe, it is an excellent thing to ſpeake well, yet for auoyding of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall Hypocriſie (I doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you) preferre good thoughts, before good words; ſpeake what you think; and ſo your thoughts being good, you cannot but ſpeake well; and thinke it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſafeſt way, to<note n="c" place="margin">In omnibus Timanthis ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, plus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligitur, quàm pingitur, &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientis eſt ſuam celare ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam, <hi>Tynd.</hi>
                  </note> ſpeake little, and thinke more: wee doe ſee dayly baſeſt things moſt plentifull.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:20214:41"/>
               <p>In your ſilence auoid the cenſure of Affectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenneſſe, and Ignorance, and then care not how little you ſpeake, but how well: it was a good ſaying, Not that which is much, is well, but that which is well, is much.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Eſſayes Do. Fran. Ba. nunc Angliae Cancell.</note>All diſcourſe ought to be like a Field, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming home to any man; vſe diſcourſe of your ſelfe ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, of others as ſparingly, neyther ſpeaking euill of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor good of your ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Affect better diſcretion in diſcourſe then Eloquence; and to ſpeake agreeable to them you deale with, then in good words or good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Quintil. inſtit. Orac. l. 7.</note>Vſe not many circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20214:42"/> before you come to the matter, for that beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth wearineſſe, and for eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing of bluntneſſe, vſe ſome preamble.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Non eſt bonum ludere cum dijs, <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </note>Priuiledge euer from your Diſcourſe, Religion, matter of State, great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, any mans preſent bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of importance, and all cauſes that deſerue<note n="g" place="margin">Crudelis eſt animi a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nis malis gaudere, &amp; non miſerere communem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam, <hi>V. Max.</hi>
                  </note> pittie, euer putting difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt<note n="h" place="margin">Nemo vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſibi tam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, vt irrideri mereatur, <hi>Faſt.</hi>
                  </note> ſaltneſſe and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in your Diſcourſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
               <p>SOmetimes lookers on ſee more then Players: ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy ſelfe to others in what thou art<note n="i" place="margin">Omnis repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſio, vel me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liores, vel cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiores nos red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, <hi>Sen.</hi> So reprehendi ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efers, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendenda <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e feceris, <hi>Auſ.</hi>
                  </note> reprooued, but in what thou art praiſed, bee thy owne Iudge, euer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting better of a ſharpe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20214:42"/> reproofe, then a ſmooth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit. When you reprooue others, obſerue that all reproofe and admonition ought to be louingly, mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſecretly, freely, and in a fit time, hauing no other end, then the loue of our Friend or Neighbour.</p>
               <p>Before you reprooue any man, know him well; ſome men are like thornes, which eaſily toucht, hurt not, but hardly and vnwarily, draw bloud from the hand; others as Nettles, if they be nicely handled, ſting and pricke, but roughly preſſed, hurt not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIIII.</head>
               <p>IT is not poſſible, but a ſelfe-conceyted man muſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20214:43"/> be a Foole:<note n="k" place="margin">Ingenioſi ſumus ad fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendum noſmet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſos, <hi>Plin. in Paneg.</hi> Ante omnia ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt teipſum exiſtimare, quiae plus nobis vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, poſſe quàm poſſumus, <hi>Sen. de tranquill. animi, l. 9.</hi>
                  </note> for that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weaning opinion he hath of himſelfe, excludes all opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of getting know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Thinke thy ſelfe but ſo bare<note n="l" place="margin">O quàm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempta res eſt homo, niſi ſupra humana ſe erexerit: putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do in exortu, bulla in omni vita, &amp; eſca vermium in morte, <hi>Theoph. Alexand. in Paſhal.</hi>
                  </note> as thou art, and more thou needeſt not; and rather confeſſe thy igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, then profeſſe the knowledge thou haſt not: it is no ſhame not to know all things, and more dangerous to ſurfet vpon wit, then want it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XV.</head>
               <p>ALl paſſions or perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Soule, (as Iealouſie, Enuie, Reuenge, Hopes, Feares, Ioyes, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, Ambition, Couet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Luſt, &amp;c.) are ſo violent, that they driue the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20214:43"/> Soule from the Seat of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and doe proceed either from Ignorance, Inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſſe, or from a falſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that the good or ill is greater then it is: therefore when any affection begins to mooue, ſtay it, and compel it to giue way to Reaſon; euer vſe your paſſions, as<note n="m" place="margin">Magni Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratores, cum vident malè pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere milites, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo labore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſcunt, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditionibus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, <hi>V. Max.</hi>
                  </note> wiſe Princes doe thoſe they miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt for faction; hold them downe, &amp; keepe them bare, that their impotencie and remiſſeneſſe may afford you ſecuritie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVI.</head>
               <p>AMong all the paſſions to which we are ſubiect, there is none more hurtfull (and more to be eſchewed) then Iealouſie, from whence
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20214:44"/> many other vehement per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations doe proceed.</p>
               <p>When we haue once ſwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the <hi>Nectar</hi> of Loue (either contracted by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued fauour to our friend, or Matrimoniall Couenant) we are ſo chary, that we can indure no Corriuall of our thoughts, neyther admit partaker of our fauours.</p>
               <p>From this feare procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the furie that men call Iealouſie, which is a ſecret ſuſpicion that eyther our friend hath not loyally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged the confidence wee had in him, or that others ſhould inioy that excellency wee haue choſen ſole and ſingular to our ſelues.</p>
               <p>This is the<note n="*" place="margin">Vita quae tandem magis eſt iucunda? Vel viris doctis magis expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda? Mente quam pura ſociam iugalem, ſemper amare. Vita quae tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem magis eſt dolenda? Vel magis cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis fugienda quam qua (Falſa ſuspecta probitate amici) tollit amorem? Nulla eam tollit medicina peſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em, Nullamue em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſtrum vel imago ſanè, Aſtra nec curant magicae nec artes Zelotypiam, <hi>ex Solon. in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d. ſept. Sapi.</hi>
                  </note> Canker that fretteth the quiet of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20214:44"/> thoughts, the Moth that conſumeth the life of man, and the Poyſon ſpecially op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed againſt the perfection of loue.</p>
               <p>After the heart is once in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with Iealouſie, the ſleeps are broken &amp; conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Dreames, and diſquiet ſlumbers; the thoughts are cares and ſorrowes; the life woe and miſerie; that liuing dies, &amp; dying prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs the life in worſe content then death.</p>
               <p>This foule and diſgraced ſtaine of Iealouſie, is as hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the heart, as a Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice to the ſight, or Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke to the taſte: and as true Loue is Diuine with Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſo is it Helliſh with Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, proceeding from the fearefull miſdoubting of not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20214:45"/> correſpondence, or exceſſe of Loue.</p>
               <p>It ſhortneth not only the life, but oftentimes is the cauſe of moſt horrible Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres.</p>
               <p>If Fortune frowne in Loue, we flye to patience; if there happen Iarres, louing and friendly brawles, are but introductions to greater delight. If Pouertie inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vene, wee relye vpon time, (knowing that all earthly things are ſubiect to viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) the loweſt ebbe may haue his flow, the deaddeſt neape his full tydes: but as the fire conſumeth Flax, ſo this infernall plague of Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie rooteth and raceth out all true loue from the heart.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:20214:45"/>
               <p>I cannot omit the aduice, that (long agoe) a iudicious (&amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Ex Relat. Flemin.</note> iouiall diſpoſed) Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman did giue to his frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, who was begunne to bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered with the burning ague of Iealouſie, and it was thus:</p>
               <p>I perceiue (ſaid he) you are much perplexed with ſome deep conceiued griefe, yet not ſo deepe, but I haue diued into it; and if you will anſwere mee directly to a queſtion, that I wil propoſe, I ſhall either cure your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, or confirme your folly; to whom the other replied, confeſſing that he was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſturbed, and as hee would anſwere his queſtion, ſo would he be glad to haue ſo skilfull a Phyſician. Then
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20214:46"/> ſaid hee, Put the caſe that Hornes you muſt haue: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will you make choice to haue them in your head, or in your pocket? The other anſwered, In my pocket. You haue anſwered rightly, ſayd his friend, and I vnderſtand partly by the report of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that haue taken notice (by your owne diſquietnes) of your diſcontent, and partly, that I ſee you tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with that paſſion, that a wiſe man neuer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits further entrance, then to his pocket.</p>
               <p>My aduice is, that you wade not where the Foord hath no footing; barke not with the Wolues of Syria, againſt the Moone; looke not to climbe to Olympus,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20214:46"/> neither aime at impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: but pacifie that with patience, which you cannot amend by being paſſionate, and rather careleſly paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, or ſecretly ſmother that which (without the hazard of your credit, and ſtayne of your Poſteritie) cannot bee proclaymed, then<note n="a" place="margin">Vt ignis, vbi foenum v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum arripue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſine mora, ſimulac materia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at tigerit, flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam lucidam accendit: Ita zelotypiae ignis, vbi animum at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigit, amorem omnem penitùs exurit, <hi>Autor de Sing.</hi>
                  </note> adde fire to ſuch combuſtible matter, that (once kindled) you are neuer able to quench.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVII.</head>
               <p>ENuie is a baſe fretting griefe, conceiued againſt the weale, or good eſtate of others, or a Helliſh ioying at the fall, or aduerſe fortune of our Neighbours; as it was the firſt weapon, wherewith man receyued his deadly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20214:47"/> blow, in Paradiſe: ſo euer ſince hath it beene ſo charily preſerued, by that irreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liable Enemie to man, that he neuer doth impart it, but to his<note n="a" place="margin">Inuidia non in alio quàm in minuto, degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri &amp; ieiuno animo ſibi domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium parat, <hi>Caſſ.</hi>
                  </note> deare friends, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrald Slaues, who once poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with this infernall fauor, will rather like <hi>Aeſops</hi> toad, by enuying others greatnes, thruſt themſelues out of their owne skinnes, then any other ſhal be either partaker of their good thoughts, or good words, howſoeuer ſome-times, (yet ſeldome) they (hypocritically) ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the<note n="b" place="margin">Detractio eſt ſtultorum theſaurus, quem in lingua geru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>Aug. in detr.</hi>
                  </note> detracting ſmoke.</p>
               <p>As I wiſh you neuer to entertayne the leaſt coale of this ſelfe-conſuming fire; ſo becauſe true vertue reſts in it ſelfe, eyther for reward or
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20214:47"/> cenſure, if you finde your ſelfe vpright,<note n="c" place="margin">In hoc flec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendi ſumus, vt omnia vulgi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia nobis ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la videantur, nam vt virtus ſualuce conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cua auxilium a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatur alienae comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dationis: Ita vulgi opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones parui facit, <hi>Sym. &amp; Claud.</hi>
                  </note> let not falſe rumours, neyther enuie of the baſe vulgar daunt you: for as the leaſt flye hath her ſpleene, the ſmall Ant her gall, ſo no<note n="d" place="margin">Vt vmbra hominem, ſic inuidia virtute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius ſequitur, <hi>Tacit.</hi>
                  </note> man vertuous, although neuer ſo meane, but hath his enuie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVIII.</head>
               <p>REuenge (beeing an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane thirſt for the bloud of man, or to do harm to others) is ſo offenſiue, that commonly it hurteth both the<note n="e" place="margin">O ſtolide fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roces, qui dum in vindictam ruitis, vitae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius &amp; aeternae diſcrimen incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritis; nonne videtis vos ſpecioſo honoris titulo ad carnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinam duci? nonne pudet vos ſingularis dementiae? non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne poenitet vos alae, periculoſi certaminis, vbi vigor ille a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi &amp; praeſtantia ingenij, <hi>Chriſtop. de cap. fon. in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomachos.</hi>
                  </note> Offrer and Suffrer; as in the Bee, the patterne of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20214:48"/> fond ſpightfulneſſe, who in her anger inuenometh the fleſh, and euer after liueth a Drone.</p>
               <p>This vindictiue paſſion, affecting reuenge,<note n="f" place="margin">Ille nefarius &amp; ſine gente, nibu<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mihi eſto, qui cupit ferum, &amp; exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crabile bellum, <hi>Hom. Il. 2.</hi>
                  </note> ciuill diſſention, and priuate quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells, hath beene the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of many ancient E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, Families, and worthie Perſonages; if they had not beene tainted with the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous note of barbarous Crueltie, Sedition, and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh maintenance of falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Alterius per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio, tua ſit cautio, <hi>Iſidor. folil. 1.</hi>
                  </note>Therefore let others harmes preuent your dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and account<note n="h" place="margin">Optima in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuria vltio, est obliuto. Nobile vincendi genus eſt patientia, <hi>Iuue.</hi>
                  </note> it a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to remit a wrong, and applaud it for true and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian valour, that you may hurt and will not, keeping
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20214:48"/> that Golden Meane, in the remitting of wrongs, that you neither incourage others to offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor induce God to retaine yours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIX.</head>
               <p>KEepe a meane in your Ioyes, Hopes, Feares, &amp; Sorrowes, and becauſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man hath his<note n="i" place="margin">Quem dies videt veniens ſuperbum, hunc dies videt fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens iacentem, <hi>Auſ.</hi>
                  </note> turne of ſorrow, before it come, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for it, when it comes,<note n="k" place="margin">Nihil mihi videtur infoe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius eo, cui nihil euenit aduerſi, <hi>Senec.</hi> Ignotae tantum foelicibus Arae, <hi>Stat. l. 12.</hi>
                  </note> welcome it, when it goes, take but halfe a farewell, ſtill expecting his returne (the greateſt part of the life of man is conſumed in hoping well, beeing ill, and fearing worſe:)<note n="l" place="margin">Si fortuna in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat, caueto tolli, ſi fortuna tonat, caueto mergi, Periand. <hi>Symbol.</hi>
                  </note> when thou art ill, liue in hope of better; when thou art well, in feare of worſe; neyther doe at any
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20214:49"/> time hope without feare (leſt thou be deceiued, with too much confide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) neither do thou feare without hope (leſt thou bee ouer-much deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) &amp; in all Feares, Hopes, and Sorrowes, bee carefull that you bee euer prouided with the true grounds of contentation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XX.</head>
               <p>TRue<note n="l" place="margin">Contemptor ambitionis &amp; infinitae poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Dominus ipſa vetuſtate flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſcit, <hi>Democ.</hi>
                  </note> Magnanimitie is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer moſt ſettled &amp; calme in greatneſſe; eſchew (as a contagious poyſon) ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being a diſordered, and inſatiable deſire of glorie, a neuer-ſatisfied greedineſſe to rule and aſpire: This vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſion, carried away by the perturbations of Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, hath beene, and is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20214:49"/> the<note n="m" place="margin">Septem illa mundi miracula (&amp; ſi his quae mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiliora) ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium annorum extruxit ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, &amp; aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſolo equata viſentur, <hi>Sen. ad Polib.</hi>
                  </note> ouerthrow of many floriſhing Eſtates, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſpirits. This Ambition is ſtil accompanied with like diſcontent in inioying, as in want; making men like poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned Rats, who when they haue taſted their bane, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſt vntill they drinke, and then much leſſe vnto their death: It is Ambition that<note n="n" place="margin">Plat. de Rep. &amp; <hi>2.</hi> de lege.</note> kindles vp the fire of Domeſticall Diuiſions, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Warres, making no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reckoning of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer damnable enterprizes, then to further her deuiſed platformes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> had a Domeſticall<note n="o" place="margin">Ex Carifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j Hiſtor. Athen. lib. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer, that did ſing daily in his eare, before hee did come out of his Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20214:50"/> Remember, <hi>Philip,</hi> thou art mortall.</p>
               <p>His ſonne <hi>Alexander,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many<note n="p" place="margin">Satis eſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſe <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro,</hi> quàm mundo lucere ſatis; ita eſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum natura, poſt omnia Oceanus, poſt Oceanum nihil; de ſiſte, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> orbis te tuus reuocat. <hi>Plut. de fort. Alex.</hi>
                  </note> famous and<note n="q" place="margin">Qui tam hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridi montes, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non iuga <hi>Alexander</hi> calcauerit? vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra liberi patris trophaea conſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; non quaeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus orbem, ſed amittimus, <hi>Sen. Suaſ. 1.</hi>
                  </note> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigable trauels, (ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with Ambition) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had conceyued in his mind, a fond opinion of his owne Deitie, and did ſtiffely maintaine it, yet on a time, when he was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a Dart, and did ſee his bloud flow out in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, he then plainly<note n="r" place="margin">Omnes homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes me deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe exiſtimant, ſed vulnus hoc, me hominem eſſe indicat, <hi>Quint. Curt. de geſt. Alex.</hi>
                  </note> did confeſſe, that hee was no more but a man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the Great fed thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Beggers, in his owne dining Chamber euery day, that by this ſad view of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, he might be mooued to a more moderation of his high fortune.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:20214:50"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hannibal,</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hannibalem</hi> ferunt frenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, gementem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, ac non ſine lachrymis, Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum verba audiſſe; rarò quequam alium, patriam exilij cauſa relinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem magis moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum abiſſe, quam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um ex hoſtili ſolo: respexiſſe ſaepe Italiae littora, deos homineſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, accuſantem; ſe quoque, ac ſuum ipſius caput excera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quod non cruentum à Cannenſi victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria militem Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam duxiſſet, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iu. Decad 3. lib. 10.</hi>
                  </note> after the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ouerthrow of <hi>Cannas,</hi> (the Ambaſſadours of his Enemie lying proſtrate at his feet) deeply conſidering the inſtabilitie of worldly affaires, did ſo checke his ambitious Deſignes, that in lieu of Triumph, he crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Victory with teares.</p>
               <p>Theſe Preſidents, and the various Spectacles of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Miſerie, the croſſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualties, which on euery ſide preſent themſelues to the eyes of the ambitious, doe aduiſe rather to liue in the Wiſemans Stocks,<note n="t" place="margin">Paruo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus, non aeget mendicitate, <hi>Plaut.</hi>
                  </note> with moderate contentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, then in a Fooles Paradiſe, to bee vexed with wilfull Vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and preſumptuous Ambition. Wherein three thoughts may curbe the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20214:51"/> moſt aſpiring mindes; the cares that accompany them, how hard it is to ſtand in ſo ſlipperie a place, and how dangerous or irrecouerable the fall is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XX.</head>
               <p>COuetouſneſſe<note n="u" place="margin">Auaritia eſt bellua fera, &amp; immanis, intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa, quae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendit oppida, agros, fana, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos vaſtat: di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uina cum huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis miſcet, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> exercitus, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> moenia obſtant, quo minùs vi ſua penetret; fama pudicitia, cunctos morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſpoliat; veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſi pecuniae &amp; vſurae decus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeris, magna illa vis auaritiae facile bonis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus vincetur, <hi>Val. Max.</hi>
                  </note> is a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall vice of the Soule, tending to an vnſatiable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to haue from all men, &amp; to with-hold vniuſtly that which belongeth to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: it is rightly compared to a Dropſie, the more it hath, the more it deſireth; or to <hi>Tantalus</hi> in Hell, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt food and Water, dieth with hunger and thirſt: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers compare a couetous man to an Hogge, that is good for nothing vntill death; or to a Dogge in a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20214:51"/> Wheele, that roſteth meate for other mens eating.</p>
               <p>As in Quicke-ſiluer, all things ſwimme but Gold, ſo nothing ſinketh to the heart of a couetous man, but gain: Pietie, Honeſtie, and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſwimme on the top, and deſcend not to the heart; a couetous mans Wiſedome conſiſts onely<note n="x" place="margin">Inſania dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi ſunt, qui tam multa anxiae co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerunt, cum ſit tam paucis opus, <hi>Demo.</hi>
                  </note> in gaine, but in more requiſite Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he is a baſe Ignorant, and is to be<note n="y" place="margin">Pla. pol. <hi>2.</hi> Ariſt. <hi>2.</hi> oeco.</note> excluded from all wel-gouerned Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths. From this Couet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, as from a Fountain of miſ-hap, proceedeth the ſubuerſion of Eſtates, the wracke of Oeconomical So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties; from thence doe iſſue Treaſons, breach of Amitie, and a million of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miſchiefes: Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20214:52"/> neyther regardeth Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, nor Equitie; it contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all Lawes, both Diuine and Humane, condemnes the Innocent, iuſtifies the Guiltie, finding euer ſome excuſe for Corruption, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, and Vſurie. Finally, it makes yong men Fooles,<note n="z" place="margin">Auaritia ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilis quid velit non intelligo: quid enim ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdius qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo minus reſtat viae plus viatici quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere? <hi>Cic. Tuſc.</hi>
                  </note> old men mad and Atheiſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXI.</head>
               <p>HE that<note n="a" place="margin">Caſſ. l. <hi>7</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> did call riches, <hi>Bona Fortunae,</hi> did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vtter his auaricious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then ſhew himſelfe a good Philoſopher, in aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing falſe goods to a falſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron; for as there is no For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to giue or guide riches, ſo there is no goodnes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; yet they are ſo neceſſary (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to good men) that<note n="b" place="margin">Haud facile emerguat quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum virtutibus obſtat res angu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta domi, <hi>Iuuc.</hi> Paupertatis v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicum incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum habere ſapientem, dixit <hi>Architas</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophus.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they can hardly put
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20214:52"/> their goodneſſe or vertue in practice, Vertue in Pouertie beeing like vnto a goodly Ship readie rigg'd, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſaile for want of wind.</p>
               <p>After you haue informed your ſelfe of the true cauſes that make Riches neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (the chiefe whereof are to ſupply your owne wants, and to inable you to doe good to others) if Riches come in your way, refuſe them not, neyther deſire them to other end, but to make them Slaues; and if neede bee, without griefe (with <hi>Socrates</hi>)<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eurip.</hi> in vita <hi>Socrat.</hi> Saepe mecum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putans, quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſque rebus clariſsimi viri magnitudinem inueniſſent, quae res, Populos, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, Ciuitates auxiſſent; ac deinde, quibus cauſis ampliſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Regna, &amp; Imperia corruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſemper bona, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mala reperiebam: Omnes victores diuitias con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempſiſſe, &amp; victos cupiuiſſe; ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aliter excellere ſe quiſquis, &amp; diuina mortalis attingere poteſt, niſi amiſſis pecuniae &amp; corporis gaudijs; &amp; animo indulgens, non aſſentando neque concupita praebendo, ſed in labore, patientia boniſque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis &amp; factis fortibus, ſe exercitando, <hi>Val. Max.</hi>
                  </note> throw them in the Sea. Perſwade thy
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20214:53"/> ſelfe, if thou make them once Maſter, thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned thy ſelf to thy own Gallies. It is a great madnes in a man, at once to make himſelfe both Slaue and Foole: although thy Chains bee of Gold, thy bondage may bee more glorious, but not leſſe miſerable.</p>
               <p>Lay not vp too much, and vtter nothing, leſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come couetous, and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, neyther ſpend all, and lay vp nothing, leſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come prodigall and poore; euer framing rather your<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t foelicitatis eſt quantum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, poſſe: ſic mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudinis, velle quantum poſsis, <hi>Plin. in Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyr. Conſtant.</hi>
                  </note> minde to your eſtate, then your eſtate to your minde, and your charges rather vnder it, then either leuell, or aboue; a man hauing meanes, may riſe with cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, but cannot fall without ſhame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:20214:53"/>
               <head>SECT. XXII.</head>
               <p>ALl Voluptuouſneſſe (gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing<note n="f" place="margin">Per volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vitia faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius ſurrepunt, <hi>Sen. Epiſt. 7.</hi> Magnum <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> audax<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium ſuſcepiſſe Graeciam, quod voluptatum &amp; cupidinum ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulachra in gymnaſijs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecraſſet, <hi>Lact. de falſ. Relig.</hi>
                  </note> entry to other Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) is valiantly to be reſiſted, beeing a delight, which tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth our ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes with falſe ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, quickly flying away, leauing behind the occaſion of Repentance, the fruits of griefe, dulling of the Spirits, the weakning of the bodie, and innumerable Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>Delight not in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of<note n="g" place="margin">Cum ſapiens <hi>Salomon</hi> fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, ſapientia non te eripuit, res eſt imperioſa <hi>Venus.</hi> Et tu Troia potens fueras, te nulla redemit Nobilitas, non te Pergamus eripuit. Tu <hi>Samſon</hi> robuſtus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, nec te tua virtus ſeruauit, fraudes ſaepe miniſtrat amor; frangebas ſcilices, ſuperabas caſtra, domabas extremos quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid erat crudele per agros: Te tamen exciſo deluſit foemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na crine, <hi>Text. diſcrib. mul.</hi> Non ita difficile eſt, ipſis cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum retibus exire, quàm <hi>Veneris</hi> perrumpere nodos, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</hi> Vita foueam, in quam alios cecidiſſe vides, <hi>Iſidor. ſoliloq. l. 1.</hi>
                  </note> ſtrange Women, neyther tye thy ſelfe to a Womans beautie, which is
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20214:54"/> like <hi>Phidea's</hi> Pictures, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt glorious to the eie, yet blemiſhed with euery breath. <hi>Dalila</hi> will ſhew, &amp; ſpeake fayre, but in the end ſhe will bereaue thee of thy ſtrength and life: ſuch Gnats will for a while make mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke about thy eares, but be ſure they will ſting in the end; for Lechery is no other thing then a furious Paſſion,<note n="h" place="margin">Ariſt. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> ſhortning the life, hurting the Vnderſtanding, darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Memorie, taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Heart, ſpoyling Beauty, weakning the ioints, ingendring <hi>Sciatica,</hi> Gouts, Giddineſſe in the Head, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, and Pox.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXIII.</head>
               <p>LEt the filiall<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Timor Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni eſt ianitor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi,</hi> Bernard. &amp; Iohan. Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le: in Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drag Ser.</note> feare of your Creatour, and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20214:54"/>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Duo animi dati a Deo cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des domeſtici, pudor &amp; timor: qui pudorem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit, beſtiae par eſt; qui timorem, beſtia peior; <hi>Bern. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. 22. 1.</hi>
                  </note> ſhame to doe euill, be the faithfull Attendants, and Doore-keepers to hold out whatſoeuer may beget either ſorrow or diſgrace. As the firſt is the beginning &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of Wiſdome: ſo good &amp; approoued<note n="l" place="margin">Tu virorum ac mulierum praecipuum fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamentum, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicitia es: tu e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim conſecratos Veſtaefocos inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, tuo praeſidio, puerilis aetatis infignia munita ſuni, tui numi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis respectu, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerus inuentae flos permanet, te cuſtode, matronalis ſtola ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietur, <hi>Val. Max.</hi>
                  </note> ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe is the Mother of good Counſell, the Gardian of Duty, the Miſtris of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, &amp; preſeruer of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, and ſhall euer bee vnto you, as faithfull a<note n="m" place="margin">Quid beatius? quid ſecurius, quàm eiuſmodi cuſtodes habere, quibus me totum refun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, quaſi alteri mihi; qui deuiare non ſinant, fraenent praecipitem, dormitantem excitent, quorum reuerentia, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentem reprimat, excedentem corrigat, conſtantia &amp; fortitudo, nutantem firmet, erigat diffidentem, fides &amp; ſanctitas, ad honeſta &amp; ſancta prouocet, <hi>Bernard. de conſid. l. 4.</hi>
                  </note> Watch, as<note n="n" place="margin">Cum <hi>Philippo</hi> (intempeſtiuè ludenti) <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipatrum</hi> venire obnunciaretur, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, alueum qua ludebat in lectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reiecit, <hi>Athen. Dipnoſop. lib. 10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Antipater</hi> was to <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon;</hi> and in the end
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20214:55"/> crown all your actions with the Crowne, that is onely due to<note n="o" place="margin">In caſſum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num agitur, ſi ante vitae ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum deſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quia fruſtra velociter currit, qui priuſquam ad metas veniat deficit, <hi>Greg. Mor. l. 2. c. 40.</hi> Non inchoanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſiquidem praemium pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, ſed perſeuerantibus, <hi>Iſidor. de ſum. bon. l. 2. c. 7.</hi> Perſeuerantia ſola virtutum coronatur, <hi>Ber.</hi>
                  </note> Perſeuerance. From this commendable ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe, many things are to be priuiledged; as, not to be aſhamed to diſpleaſe the multitude againſt Reaſon and Equitie; not to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to reprooue ſuch as come of purpoſe to offend; not to bee aſhamed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your Ignorance, that you may be inſtructed; or if any man with-hold your due, bee not aſhamed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it with Reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIIII.</head>
               <p>EVer<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apelli</hi> fuit perpetua conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudo, nunquam tam occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam diem agendi, vt non lineam ducendo exerceret artem; &amp; vſu pinxit <hi>Apelles</hi> quae pingi non poſſunt, tonitrua, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura, <hi>Plin. l. 35.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> accuſtome your ſelfe to good things: for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20214:55"/> three things concurre to make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perfect; Nature, Education, &amp; Cuſtome: the laſt two are of force to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule what is amiſſe in the firſt, and that which is called<note n="q" place="margin">Habitus eſt altera natura, <hi>Sim.</hi>
                  </note> habit, (beeing a conſtant deſire, and following or eſchewing of things) is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by cuſtome, then which, there is nothing of greater force, either to good, or ill; vnleſſe you attaine to this habit of goodneſſe, your ſoule worketh in vaine, or like an vnskilfull Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice; for when our actions and affections are growne to a habit, then are they called, eyther Vertues or Vices, as they are well or ill done.</p>
               <p>This habit in bewitching Vices, is<note n="r" place="margin">Vbi ſemel decratum eſt, in praeceps perueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; adeo matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rè à rectis in praua, à prauis in praecipitia peruenitur, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere. lib. 2.</hi>
                  </note> hardly, or<note n="ſ" place="margin">Tunc conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata infoelicitas eſt, vbi turpia non ſolùm dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant, ſed pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, <hi>Senec.</hi>
                  </note> neuer remoued: therefore the beſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20214:56"/> remedie againſt ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous an euill, is to reſiſt the beginning of vicious moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Nam turpius eijcitur, quàm non admittitur hoſpes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXV.</head>
               <p>MY laſt aduice vnto you, concerning the right vſe of all the Cardinall Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, &amp; eſchewing their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries, ſhall be borrowed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, l. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> of this Age; which is, that you make ouer all Vertues, Temperance Queene; I doe not meane the vulgar interpretation of Temperance, conſiſting <hi>in gustu, &amp; Tactu,</hi> or modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe two Senſes; but of that wiſe moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, firſt, commanding your ſelfe, then as a Queene ſhall ouer-rule all the affections
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20214:56"/> of your mind, and as a wiſe Phyſician, mixe all your Actions accordingly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
               <p>Remember, that in all commendable Actions, <hi>In medio ſtat virtus;</hi> and that the<note n="u" place="margin">Pro bonis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la amplectimur, vitia nobis ſub virtutis nomine obrepunt, ſunt enim vitia vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutibus vicina, <hi>Hier. lib. 3. de Vict.</hi>
                  </note> two Vices, at eyther end of them, are but falſly coloured vnder the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed names of Vertue, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing indeed no affinitie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXVI.</head>
               <p>BEe carefull to frame all your outward Actions, (whether they be neceſſary; as feeding, ſleeping, ſpeaking, geſture, &amp;c. or not neceſſary, although conuenient, as ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and all ſort of lawfull recreation,)<note n="x" place="margin">Cura vt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas mentem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam in corpore ſano, <hi>Auſ.</hi> Animi imperio corporis ſeruitio magis vtimur, <hi>Saluſt. Catil. lib. 1.</hi> Corpus, dum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtra animae deputatur, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors &amp; cohaeres inuenitur, <hi>Tert. lib. 2. cap. 7.</hi> Omnis nimietas vitium reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>Tynd.</hi>
                  </note> that they may ſerue, for the aduancement
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20214:57"/> of your inward Vertues, diſpoſition and health of your body; and as they that ſhould eate ſome Diſh deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſweete, temper it with tarte ſawce (leſt they bee cloyed,) and thoſe that receiue bitter Pills, rowle them in Sugar (that they may not bee annoyed with the vnpleaſant taſte:) ſo, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeaſon all your exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Actions with Mediocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, then with Delight or Exceſſe.</p>
               <p>But becauſe all theſe ſorts of outward Actions haue beene ſo fully intreated of by many, and are (I doe hope) knowne to all (that I come to an end) I will only adde a ſhort aduice, for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Bookes, for Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell and Trauell, being three
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20214:57"/> of the former indifferent Actions, whereof you may make much profitable vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXVII.</head>
               <p>THe chiefe vſe of Bookes, is to increaſe knowledge, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme iudgement, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare times paſt with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; to draw profit from both for the future, and to bring out the dead ſpeaking with the liuing. Bookes are the moſt free Reproouers of Vice, the moſt truſtie and comfortable Friends, and faithfull Companions that are, euer readie with good counſell, when it is either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired or needfull; they are the onely Phyſicke to purge the naturall dulneſſe of our home-bred ignorance, and weake capacitie.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:20214:58"/>
               <p>In reading of Bookes it is better (as in the vſe of Friends) to conuerſe ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with few, then to wander amongſt many without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit.</p>
               <p>Make choyce of the beſt<note n="y" place="margin">Faſtidientis ſtomachi eſt multa deguſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, <hi>Plut.</hi> Vt cibos dimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quo facilius digerantur, ita lectio non cruda ſed multa itera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione mollita, memoriae imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tradatur, nec per partes ſcruta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da omnia, ſed perlectus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendus, <hi>Quint. inſtit. Orat. lib. 11. cap. 2.</hi>
                  </note> Authors that write vpon the ſubiect you moſt affect, or is moſt neceſſary for you; (euer reiecting all ſuch as are either repugnant to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or good Manners) reade them with diligence, not in parcels (as many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably doe) or ſlightly, and then caſt them aſide: but pervſe them with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent obſeruation orderly, from beginning to end; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſtrict account of your ſelfe, of thoſe things you reade: ſo ſhall your labours (by exerciſe &amp; daily increaſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20214:58"/> of your knowledge) at laſt produce the deſired fruit of your ſtudies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXVIII.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the inward diſpoſition of the mind may be ſooner diſcouered, then by light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or ſtayedneſſe of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell; a phantaſticall attyre being a confirmation of an vnſettled mind.<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>l. 3. fol. 110.</hi> Dent tibi <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> aetatem dij quam mereris, ſeruent<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum quem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt, <hi>Plin. in Panegyr.</hi> Ampliora ſunt merita Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum, quàm no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum optatae votorum, <hi>Naz. in Paneg. Conſt.</hi>
                  </note> I doe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you, not to follow the frantike humours of new Faſhions, neyther to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly, baſely, ſlightly clothed, nor artificially dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; but to vſe your clothes in a cleanly, honeſt, comely, and careleſſe forme.</p>
               <p>At ſuch times as you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with your Superiours, or Strangers, rather be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20214:59"/> then vnder the rate, your meanes will allow you for apparell: although it bee a great folly in a man, to iudge the preciouſneſſe of a Iewell, by the Caſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is kept, and much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to eſteeme it by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the Caſe; euen ſo by the ſame reaſon, it is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual indiſcretion to eſtimate a mans worth, either by his bodie or clothes; yet on the other ſide it is an ineuitable certaintie, that not only the common people and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, but euen wiſemen are mooued, and ſtirred vp with outward ſhewes, and their minde (according to thoſe exterior things) prepared to receiue a deepe impreſſion of liking or diſliking, fauour, or disfauour, reuerence, or
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20214:59"/> careleſſe retchleſſeneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXIX.</head>
               <p>I Doe thinke verily, that all purpoſe of Trauell vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, <hi>Non ad voluptatem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lùm, ſed ad vtilitatem,</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an induſtrious and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous minde, and that their ſpirits are more baſe, that ſtriue to houer about home, and theſe more Noble and Diuine, that imitate the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and ioy in motion.</p>
               <p>At ſuch time, therefore, as you trauel out of your Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, reſolue to trauell out of your Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie-Faſhions, and indeed out of your ſelf, that is, out of all former exceſſe of intemperate feeding, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate drinking, thriftleſſe gaming, fruitleſſe time-ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, violent exerciſing, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:20214:60"/> all irregular miſ-gouerning: determine that the end of your Trauell, is the ripening of your knowledge, and the end of your knowlege, is the<note n="a" place="margin">Exomnibus rebus humanis nihil eſt praecla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, quàm de Repub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ica bene mereri, <hi>Cicero Epiſt. 10. ad Familiar.</hi>
                  </note> ſeruice of your Countrie, which by right challengeth a chiefe intereſt in you.</p>
               <p>The firſt ſteppe to this knowledge, is to vnderſtand the Languages where you Trauell: the beſt way to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to the knowledge of them, is by Booke; for ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, practice, and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation are more helpfull. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome few Moneths (<note n="b" place="margin">Viſus viſu volatus, volatu, differt, haud e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lut, &amp; Cicades, Aquilae, &amp; Perdices ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer volant, <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
                  </note> as you find your ſelfe capable) leaue the Booke, and onely vſe your Maſter to talke with. In <hi>France, Orleance,</hi> and <hi>Bloyz,</hi> in <hi>Italie, Florence,</hi> or <hi>Sciena,</hi> in <hi>Tuſcanie, Prato,</hi> in <hi>Germanie, Hiddleburgh</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:20214:60"/> and <hi>Lipſwick,</hi> are the beſt places for the Languages.</p>
               <p>In your Trauels diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerue what you ſee in the parts you trauell, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king choyce of the beſt, and leauing the world behind you: for helping your<note n="c" place="margin">Memoria res eſt, ex omnibus partibus animi, maximè delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; fragilis, <hi>Rhod. l. 10. c. 18</hi>
                  </note> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, let your chiefe Booke be a Iournall, wherein write downe the diuers Prouinces you paſſe by, their Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, Townes, manner of Buildings, the names and benefit of the Riuers, the diſtance of Places, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Soyle, the Manners of the People, and whatſoeuer notable thing your eye encountreth by the way.</p>
               <p>In your Trauell haue ſpeciall care of your compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and friends; in that time
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20214:61"/> remember that <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pitheas</hi> are dead; neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſo much of your owne ſufficiencie, as to neglect the benefit of counſell, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome-times a young man may proue a <hi>Lelius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Rara auis in terris,</hi> yet take a young man rather for your Companion then Friend:<note n="d" place="margin">Pietas in Deum toto cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis timore (quaſi culmen &amp; Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Virtutum) ſeruetur, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phil. Alex. de Conſtant.</hi>
                  </note> ſerue God daily with great Deuotion; he is the onely Pillar to hold you vp amongſt the dangers that ſhall inuiron you.</p>
               <p>At your returne, leaue all ſtrange forrain Manners, and faſhion your ſelfe, your Manners, Apparell, Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, Conference and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation to the beſt pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of the place from whence thou diddeſt begin thy Trauels:<note n="e" place="margin">Alij ſatis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xiſſe te viſo, te recepto, alij ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis eſſe viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, <hi>Plin. in Paneg.</hi>
                  </note> ſo ſhall the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:20214:61"/> remembrance of them bee pleaſant and profitable, and thy returne an Ornament to thy Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXX.</head>
               <p>NOw<note n="f" place="margin">EPILOGVS.</note> to truſſe<note n="g" place="margin">Quod matres facere ſolent cum poma bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laria, vel tale quidpiam in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilem ſinum immiſerint, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid excidat contrahens vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuniculam cingulo ſubijci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt: idem &amp; nos faciamus orationem in longum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractam contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hamus, &amp; in memoriae cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam depona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, <hi>Chryſoſt. de Ozia, Ser. 3.</hi>
                  </note> vp all in few words: in the firſt part of that which you haue heard, is contayned a ſhort way to heauenly Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for ſetting you forward in this Iourney, the neceſſitie of a good reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt men is ſet downe, and how it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, how dangerous a<note n="h" place="margin">Quicquid praeter opinionem euenire in bello poteſt, priuſquam ingrediare cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, <hi>Thucid. li. 3.</hi>
                  </note> warrefare you are to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake in the way, and with what enemies.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of a Wiſeman forged
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:20214:62"/> vpon the Anuill of Gods Grace, are the onely Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons eyther to foyle theſe enemies, or withſtand their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er ceaſing aſſaults.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, what<note n="i" place="margin">Aci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum paritèr pugnantium quae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enda, vbi tot ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t auxil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> rij quot a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Bonauent. diet. Salut.</hi>
                  </note> auxiliarie Souldiers you ſhall chooſe, for maintenance of ſo long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Wars; and how you ſhall keepe them from mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, a diſcouerie of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ambuſcadoes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impediments that may obui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te you in ſo dangerous a March.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, ſome few helpes that will ſerue for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary prouiſion to your Campe.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Tri-vni Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20214:62"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
